<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE gutplay SYSTEM "gutplay1.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="gutplay1.css"?>

<gutplay>

<gutblurb>

<para>*The Project Gutenberg Etext of Lady Windermere's Fan, by Wilde*
#5 in our series by Oscar Wilde</para>

<para>Copyright laws are changing all over the world, be sure to check
the copyright laws for your country before posting these files!!</para>

<para>Please take a look at the important information in this header.
We encourage you to keep this file on your own disk, keeping an
electronic path open for the next readers.  Do not remove this.</para>

<para>**Welcome To The World of Free Plain Vanilla Electronic Texts**</para>

<para>**Etexts Readable By Both Humans and By Computers, Since 1971**</para>

<para>*These Etexts Prepared By Hundreds of Volunteers and Donations*</para>

<para>Information on contacting Project Gutenberg to get Etexts, and
further information is included below.  We need your donations.</para>

<para>Lady Windermere's Fan</para>

<para>by Oscar Wilde</para>

<para>January, 1997  [Etext #790]</para>

<para>*The Project Gutenberg Etext of Lady Windermere's Fan, by Wilde*
******This file should be named lwfan10.txt or lwfan10.zip******</para>

<para>Corrected EDITIONS of our etexts get a new NUMBER, lwfan11.txt.
VERSIONS based on separate sources get new LETTER, lwfan10a.txt.</para>

<para>Scanned and proofed by David Price </para>

<para>We are now trying to release all our books one month in advance
of the official release dates, for time for better editing.</para>

<para>Please note:  neither this list nor its contents are final till
midnight of the last day of the month of any such announcement.
The official release date of all Project Gutenberg Etexts is at
Midnight, Central Time, of the last day of the stated month.  A
preliminary version may often be posted for suggestion, comment
and editing by those who wish to do so.  To be sure you have an
up to date first edition [xxxxx10x.xxx] please check file sizes
in the first week of the next month.  Since our ftp program has
a bug in it that scrambles the date [tried to fix and failed] a
look at the file size will have to do, but we will try to see a
new copy has at least one byte more or less.</para>

<para>Information about Project Gutenberg (one page)</para>

<para>We produce about two million dollars for each hour we work.  The
fifty hours is one conservative estimate for how long it we take
to get any etext selected, entered, proofread, edited, copyright
searched and analyzed, the copyright letters written, etc.  This
projected audience is one hundred million readers.  If our value
per text is nominally estimated at one dollar then we produce $2
million dollars per hour this year as we release thirty-two text
files per month:  or 400 more Etexts in 1996 for a total of 800.
If these reach just 10% of the computerized population, then the
total should reach 80 billion Etexts.</para>

<para>The Goal of Project Gutenberg is to Give Away One Trillion Etext
Files by the December 31, 2001.  [10,000 x 100,000,000=Trillion]
This is ten thousand titles each to one hundred million readers,
which is only 10% of the present number of computer users.  2001
should have at least twice as many computer users as that, so it
will require us reaching less than 5% of the users in 2001.</para>

<para>We need your donations more than ever!</para>

<para>All donations should be made to "Project Gutenberg/BU":  and are
tax deductible to the extent allowable by law. (BU = Benedictine
University).  (Subscriptions to our paper newsletter go to BU.)</para>

<para>For these and other matters, please mail to:</para>

<para>Project Gutenberg
P. O. Box  2782
Champaign, IL 61825</para>

<para>When all other email fails try our Executive Director:
Michael S. Hart &lt;hart@pobox.com></para>

<para>We would prefer to send you this information by email
(Internet, Bitnet, Compuserve, ATTMAIL or MCImail).</para>

<para>******
If you have an FTP program (or emulator), please
FTP directly to the Project Gutenberg archives:
[Mac users, do NOT point and click. . .type]</para>

<para>ftp uiarchive.cso.uiuc.edu
login:  anonymous
password:  your@login
cd etext/etext90 through /etext96
or cd etext/articles [get suggest gut for more information]
dir [to see files]
get or mget [to get files. . .set bin for zip files]
GET INDEX?00.GUT
for a list of books
and
GET NEW GUT for general information
and
MGET GUT* for newsletters.</para>

<para>**Information prepared by the Project Gutenberg legal advisor**
(Three Pages)</para>

<para>***START**THE SMALL PRINT!**FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN ETEXTS**START***
Why is this "Small Print!" statement here?  You know: lawyers.
They tell us you might sue us if there is something wrong with
your copy of this etext, even if you got it for free from
someone other than us, and even if what's wrong is not our
fault.  So, among other things, this "Small Print!" statement
disclaims most of our liability to you.  It also tells you how
you can distribute copies of this etext if you want to.</para>

<para>*BEFORE!* YOU USE OR READ THIS ETEXT
By using or reading any part of this PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm
etext, you indicate that you understand, agree to and accept
this "Small Print!" statement.  If you do not, you can receive
a refund of the money (if any) you paid for this etext by
sending a request within 30 days of receiving it to the person
you got it from.  If you received this etext on a physical
medium (such as a disk), you must return it with your request.</para>

<para>ABOUT PROJECT GUTENBERG-TM ETEXTS
This PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext, like most PROJECT GUTENBERG-
tm etexts, is a "public domain" work distributed by Professor
Michael S. Hart through the Project Gutenberg Association at
Benedictine University (the "Project").  Among other
things, this means that no one owns a United States copyright
on or for this work, so the Project (and you!) can copy and
distribute it in the United States without permission and
without paying copyright royalties.  Special rules, set forth
below, apply if you wish to copy and distribute this etext
under the Project's "PROJECT GUTENBERG" trademark.</para>

<para>To create these etexts, the Project expends considerable
efforts to identify, transcribe and proofread public domain
works.  Despite these efforts, the Project's etexts and any
medium they may be on may contain "Defects".  Among other
things, Defects may take the form of incomplete, inaccurate or
corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other
intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged
disk or other etext medium, a computer virus, or computer
codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment.</para>

<para>LIMITED WARRANTY; DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES
But for the "Right of Replacement or Refund" described below,
[1] the Project (and any other party you may receive this
etext from as a PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext) disclaims all
liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including
legal fees, and [2] YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE OR
UNDER STRICT LIABILITY, OR FOR BREACH OF WARRANTY OR CONTRACT,
INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE
OR INCIDENTAL DAMAGES, EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE
POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.</para>

<para>If you discover a Defect in this etext within 90 days of
receiving it, you can receive a refund of the money (if any)
you paid for it by sending an explanatory note within that
time to the person you received it from.  If you received it
on a physical medium, you must return it with your note, and
such person may choose to alternatively give you a replacement
copy.  If you received it electronically, such person may
choose to alternatively give you a second opportunity to
receive it electronically.</para>

<para>THIS ETEXT IS OTHERWISE PROVIDED TO YOU "AS-IS".  NO OTHER
WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, ARE MADE TO YOU AS
TO THE ETEXT OR ANY MEDIUM IT MAY BE ON, INCLUDING BUT NOT
LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A
PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</para>

<para>Some states do not allow disclaimers of implied warranties or
the exclusion or limitation of consequential damages, so the
above disclaimers and exclusions may not apply to you, and you
may have other legal rights.</para>

<para>INDEMNITY
You will indemnify and hold the Project, its directors,
officers, members and agents harmless from all liability, cost
and expense, including legal fees, that arise directly or
indirectly from any of the following that you do or cause:
[1] distribution of this etext, [2] alteration, modification,
or addition to the etext, or [3] any Defect.</para>

<para>DISTRIBUTION UNDER "PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm"
You may distribute copies of this etext electronically, or by
disk, book or any other medium if you either delete this
"Small Print!" and all other references to Project Gutenberg,
or:</para>

<para>[1]  Only give exact copies of it.  Among other things, this
     requires that you do not remove, alter or modify the
     etext or this "small print!" statement.  You may however,
     if you wish, distribute this etext in machine readable
     binary, compressed, mark-up, or proprietary form,
     including any form resulting from conversion by word pro-
     cessing or hypertext software, but only so long as
     *EITHER*:</para>

<para>     [*]  The etext, when displayed, is clearly readable, and
          does *not* contain characters other than those
          intended by the author of the work, although tilde
          (~), asterisk (*) and underline (_) characters may
          be used to convey punctuation intended by the
          author, and additional characters may be used to
          indicate hypertext links; OR</para>

<para>     [*]  The etext may be readily converted by the reader at
          no expense into plain ASCII, EBCDIC or equivalent
          form by the program that displays the etext (as is
          the case, for instance, with most word processors);
          OR</para>

<para>     [*]  You provide, or agree to also provide on request at
          no additional cost, fee or expense, a copy of the
          etext in its original plain ASCII form (or in EBCDIC
          or other equivalent proprietary form).</para>

<para>[2]  Honor the etext refund and replacement provisions of this
     "Small Print!" statement.</para>

<para>[3]  Pay a trademark license fee to the Project of 20% of the
     net profits you derive calculated using the method you
     already use to calculate your applicable taxes.  If you
     don't derive profits, no royalty is due.  Royalties are
     payable to "Project Gutenberg Association / Benedictine
     University" within the 60 days following each
     date you prepare (or were legally required to prepare)
     your annual (or equivalent periodic) tax return.</para>

<para>WHAT IF YOU *WANT* TO SEND MONEY EVEN IF YOU DON'T HAVE TO?
The Project gratefully accepts contributions in money, time,
scanning machines, OCR software, public domain etexts, royalty
free copyright licenses, and every other sort of contribution
you can think of.  Money should be paid to "Project Gutenberg
Association / Benedictine University".</para>

<para>*END*THE SMALL PRINT! FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN ETEXTS*Ver.04.29.93*END*</para>

<para>Lady Windermere's Fan by Oscar Wilde
Scanned and proofed by David Price 
ccx074@coventry.ac.uk</para>

</gutblurb>

<markupblurb>
Markup by Donna Smillie for the HTML Writers Guild
Email dms@zetnet.co.uk
5 February 2000
</markupblurb>

<play>

<acknowledge>Project Gutenberg and the HTML Writers Guild. XML markup by Donna Smillie. February 2000. Etext scanned and proofed by David Price.</acknowledge>

<frontmatter>

<titlepage>

<title>Lady Windermere's Fan</title>

</titlepage>

<personae>

<title>THE PERSONS OF THE PLAY</title>

<pgroup>
<persona>Lord Windermere</persona>
<persona>Lord Darlington</persona>
<persona>Lord Augustus Lorton</persona>
<persona>Mr. Dumby</persona>
<persona>Mr. Cecil Graham</persona>
<persona>Mr. Hopper</persona>
<persona>Parker, Butler</persona>
</pgroup>

<pgroup>
<persona>Lady Windermere</persona>
<persona>The Duchess of Berwick</persona>
<persona>Lady Agatha Carlisle</persona>
<persona>Lady Plymdale</persona>
<persona>Lady Stutfield</persona>
<persona>Lady Jedburgh</persona>
<persona>Mrs. Cowper-Cowper</persona>
<persona>Mrs. Erlynne</persona>
<persona>Rosalie, Maid</persona>
</pgroup>

</personae>

<toc>

<title>THE SCENES OF THE PLAY</title>

<list>
<item>ACT I.    Morning-room in Lord Windermere's house.</item>
<item>ACT II.   Drawing-room in Lord Windermere's house.</item>
<item>ACT III.  Lord Darlington's rooms.</item>
<item>ACT IV.   Morning-room in Lord Windermere's house.</item>
</list>

</toc>

<introduction>

<para>TIME:     1892</para>
<para>PLACE:    London</para>

<para>The action of the play takes place within twenty-four hours, 
beginning on a Tuesday afternoon at five o'clock, and ending the 
next day at 1.30 p.m.</para>

</introduction>

<htitlepage>

<title>Lady Windermere's Fan</title>

</htitlepage>

</frontmatter>

<playbody>

<act>

<title>FIRST ACT</title>

<scndesc>SCENE
Morning-room of Lord Windermere's house in Carlton House Terrace.  
Doors C. and R.  Bureau with books and papers R.  Sofa with small 
tea-table L.  Window opening on to terrace L.  Table R.
[C = Center, L = Left, R = Right]</scndesc>

<stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE is at table R., arranging roses in a blue bowl.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Is your ladyship at home this afternoon?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes - who has called?</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Lord Darlington, my lady.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Hesitates for a moment.]</stagedir>  Show him up - and I'm 
at home to any one who calls.</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Yes, my lady.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It's best for me to see him before to-night.  I'm 
glad he's come.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Lord Darlington,</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD DARLINGTON C.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  How do you do, Lady Windermere?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How do you do, Lord Darlington?  No, I can't 
shake hands with you.  My hands are all wet with these roses.  
Aren't they lovely?  They came up from Selby this morning.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  They are quite perfect.  <stagedir>[Sees a fan lying on the 
table.]</stagedir>  And what a wonderful fan!  May I look at it?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Do.  Pretty, isn't it!  It's got my name on it, 
and everything.  I have only just seen it myself.  It's my 
husband's birthday present to me.  You know to-day is my birthday?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  No?  Is it really?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, I'm of age to-day.  Quite an important day 
in my life, isn't it?  That is why I am giving this party tonight.  
Do sit down.  <stagedir>[Still arranging flowers.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Sitting down.]</stagedir>  I wish I had known it was your 
birthday, Lady Windermere.  I would have covered the whole street 
in front of your house with flowers for you to walk on.  They are 
made for you.  <stagedir>[A short pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Lord Darlington, you annoyed me last night at the 
Foreign Office.  I am afraid you are going to annoy me again.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I, Lady Windermere?</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER and FOOTMAN C., with tray and tea things.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Put it there, Parker.  That will do.  <stagedir>[Wipes her 
hands with her pocket-handkerchief, goes to tea-table, and sits 
down.]</stagedir>  Won't you come over, Lord Darlington?</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Takes chair and goes across L.C.]</stagedir>  I am quite 
miserable, Lady Windermere.  You must tell me what I did.  <stagedir>[Sits 
down at table L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Well, you kept paying me elaborate compliments 
the whole evening.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  Ah, nowadays we are all of us so hard 
up, that the only pleasant things to pay ARE compliments.  They're 
the only things we CAN pay.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Shaking her head.]</stagedir>  No, I am talking very 
seriously.  You mustn't laugh, I am quite serious.  I don't like 
compliments, and I don't see why a man should think he is pleasing 
a woman enormously when he says to her a whole heap of things that 
he doesn't mean.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Ah, but I did mean them.  <stagedir>[Takes tea which she 
offers him.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Gravely.]</stagedir>  I hope not.  I should be sorry to 
have to quarrel with you, Lord Darlington.  I like you very much, 
you know that.  But I shouldn't like you at all if I thought you 
were what most other men are.  Believe me, you are better than most 
other men, and I sometimes think you pretend to be worse.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  We all have our little vanities, Lady Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why do you make that your special one?  <stagedir>[Still 
seated at table L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Still seated L.C.]</stagedir>  Oh, nowadays so many 
conceited people go about Society pretending to be good, that I 
think it shows rather a sweet and modest disposition to pretend to 
be bad.  Besides, there is this to be said.  If you pretend to be 
good, the world takes you very seriously.  If you pretend to be 
bad, it doesn't.  Such is the astounding stupidity of optimism.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Don't you WANT the world to take you seriously 
then, Lord Darlington?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  No, not the world.  Who are the people the world 
takes seriously?  All the dull people one can think of, from the 
Bishops down to the bores.  I should like YOU to take me very 
seriously, Lady Windermere, YOU more than any one else in life.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why - why me?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[After a slight hesitation.]</stagedir>  Because I think we 
might be great friends.  Let us be great friends.  You may want a 
friend some day.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why do you say that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Oh! - we all want friends at times.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I think we're very good friends already, Lord 
Darlington.  We can always remain so as long as you don't -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Don't what?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Don't spoil it by saying extravagant silly things 
to me.  You think I am a Puritan, I suppose?  Well, I have 
something of the Puritan in me.  I was brought up like that.  I am 
glad of it.  My mother died when I was a mere child.  I lived 
always with Lady Julia, my father's elder sister, you know.  She 
was stern to me, but she taught me what the world is forgetting, 
the difference that there is between what is right and what is 
wrong.  SHE allowed of no compromise.  I allow of none.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  My dear Lady Windermere!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Leaning back on the sofa.]</stagedir>  You look on me as 
being behind the age. - Well, I am!  I should be sorry to be on the 
same level as an age like this.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You think the age very bad?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  Nowadays people seem to look on life as a 
speculation.  It is not a speculation.  It is a sacrament.  Its 
ideal is Love.  Its purification is sacrifice.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  Oh, anything is better than being 
sacrificed!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Leaning forward.]</stagedir>  Don't say that.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I do say it.  I feel it - I know it.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  The men want to know if they are to put the carpets on the 
terrace for to-night, my lady?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You don't think it will rain, Lord Darlington, do 
you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I won't hear of its raining on your birthday!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Tell them to do it at once, Parker.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Still seated.]</stagedir>  Do you think then - of course I 
am only putting an imaginary instance - do you think that in the 
case of a young married couple, say about two years married, if the 
husband suddenly becomes the intimate friend of a woman of - well, 
more than doubtful character - is always calling upon her, lunching 
with her, and probably paying her bills - do you think that the 
wife should not console herself?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Frowning]</stagedir>  Console herself?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Yes, I think she should - I think she has the 
right.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Because the husband is vile - should the wife be 
vile also?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Vileness is a terrible word, Lady Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It is a terrible thing, Lord Darlington.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Do you know I am afraid that good people do a 
great deal of harm in this world.  Certainly the greatest harm they 
do is that they make badness of such extraordinary importance.  It 
is absurd to divide people into good and bad.  People are either 
charming or tedious.  I take the side of the charming, and you, 
Lady Windermere, can't help belonging to them.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Now, Lord Darlington.  <stagedir>[Rising and crossing R., 
front of him.]</stagedir>  Don't stir, I am merely going to finish my flowers.  
<stagedir>[Goes to table R.C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising and moving chair.]</stagedir>  And I must say I 
think you are very hard on modern life, Lady Windermere.  Of course 
there is much against it, I admit.  Most women, for instance, 
nowadays, are rather mercenary.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Don't talk about such people.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Well then, setting aside mercenary people, who, 
of course, are dreadful, do you think seriously that women who have 
committed what the world calls a fault should never be forgiven?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Standing at table.]</stagedir>  I think they should never 
be forgiven.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  And men?  Do you think that there should be the 
same laws for men as there are for women?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Certainly!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I think life too complex a thing to be settled by 
these hard and fast rules.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  If we had 'these hard and fast rules,' we should 
find life much more simple.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You allow of no exceptions?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  None!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Ah, what a fascinating Puritan you are, Lady 
Windermere!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  The adjective was unnecessary, Lord Darlington.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I couldn't help it.  I can resist everything 
except temptation.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You have the modern affectation of weakness.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Looking at her.]</stagedir>  It's only an affectation, Lady 
Windermere.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  The Duchess of Berwick and Lady Agatha Carlisle.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter the DUCHESS OF BERWICK and LADY AGATHA CARLISLE C.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coming down C., and shaking hands.]</stagedir>  Dear 
Margaret, I am so pleased to see you.  You remember Agatha, don't 
you?  <stagedir>[Crossing L.C.]</stagedir>  How do you do, Lord Darlington?  I won't let 
you know my daughter, you are far too wicked.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Don't say that, Duchess.  As a wicked man I am a 
complete failure.  Why, there are lots of people who say I have 
never really done anything wrong in the whole course of my life.  
Of course they only say it behind my back.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Isn't he dreadful?  Agatha, this is Lord 
Darlington.  Mind you don't believe a word he says.  <stagedir>[LORD 
DARLINGTON crosses R.C.]</stagedir>  No, no tea, thank you, dear.  <stagedir>[Crosses 
and sits on sofa.]</stagedir>  We have just had tea at Lady Markby's.  Such 
bad tea, too.  It was quite undrinkable.  I wasn't at all 
surprised.  Her own son-in-law supplies it.  Agatha is looking 
forward so much to your ball to-night, dear Margaret.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Seated L.C.]</stagedir>  Oh, you mustn't think it is going 
to be a ball, Duchess.  It is only a dance in honour of my 
birthday.  A small and early.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Standing L.C.]</stagedir>  Very small, very early, and very 
select, Duchess.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[On sofa L.]</stagedir>  Of course it's going to be 
select.  But we know THAT, dear Margaret, about YOUR house.  It is 
really one of the few houses in London where I can take Agatha, and 
where I feel perfectly secure about dear Berwick.  I don't know 
what society is coming to.  The most dreadful people seem to go 
everywhere.  They certainly come to my parties - the men get quite 
furious if one doesn't ask them.  Really, some one should make a 
stand against it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I will, Duchess.  I will have no one in my house 
about whom there is any scandal.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.C.]</stagedir>  Oh, don't say that, Lady Windermere.  I 
should never be admitted!  <stagedir>[Sitting.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Oh, men don't matter.  With women it is 
different.  We're good.  Some of us are, at least.  But we are 
positively getting elbowed into the corner.  Our husbands would 
really forget our existence if we didn't nag at them from time to 
time, just to remind them that we have a perfect legal right to do 
so.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  It's a curious thing, Duchess, about the game of 
marriage - a game, by the way, that is going out of fashion - the 
wives hold all the honours, and invariably lose the odd trick.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>   The odd trick?  Is that the husband, Lord 
Darlington?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  It would be rather a good name for the modern 
husband.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Dear Lord Darlington, how thoroughly depraved 
you are!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Lord Darlington is trivial.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Ah, don't say that, Lady Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why do you TALK so trivially about life, then?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Because I think that life is far too important a 
thing ever to talk seriously about it.  <stagedir>[Moves up C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  What does he mean?  Do, as a concession to my 
poor wits, Lord Darlington, just explain to me what you really 
mean.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coming down back of table.]</stagedir>  I think I had 
better not, Duchess.  Nowadays to be intelligible is to be found 
out.  Good-bye!  <stagedir>[Shakes hands with DUCHESS.]</stagedir>  And now - <stagedir>[goes up 
stage]</stagedir> Lady Windermere, good-bye.  I may come to-night, mayn't I?  
Do let me come.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Standing up stage with LORD DARLINGTON.]</stagedir>  Yes, 
certainly.  But you are not to say foolish, insincere things to 
people.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  Ah! you are beginning to reform me.  
It is a dangerous thing to reform any one, Lady Windermere.  <stagedir>[Bows, 
and exit C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Who has risen, goes C.]</stagedir>  What a charming, 
wicked creature!  I like him so much.  I'm quite delighted he's 
gone!  How sweet you're looking!  Where DO you get your gowns?  And 
now I must tell you how sorry I am for you, dear Margaret.  
<stagedir>[Crosses to sofa and sits with LADY WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  Agatha, darling!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.  <stagedir>[Rises.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Will you go and look over the photograph album 
that I see there?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.  <stagedir>[Goes to table up L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Dear girl!  She is so fond of photographs of 
Switzerland.  Such a pure taste, I think.  But I really am so sorry 
for you, Margaret</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  Why, Duchess?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Oh, on account of that horrid woman.  She 
dresses so well, too, which makes it much worse, sets such a 
dreadful example.  Augustus - you know my disreputable brother - 
such a trial to us all - well, Augustus is completely infatuated 
about her.  It is quite scandalous, for she is absolutely 
inadmissible into society.  Many a woman has a past, but I am told 
that she has at least a dozen, and that they all fit.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Whom are you talking about, Duchess?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  About Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne?  I never heard of her, Duchess.  
And what HAS she to do with me?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  My poor child!  Agatha, darling!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Will you go out on the terrace and look at the 
sunset?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.  <stagedir>[Exit through window, L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Sweet girl!  So devoted to sunsets!  Shows 
such refinement of feeling, does it not?  After all, there is 
nothing like Nature, is there?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  But what is it, Duchess?  Why do you talk to me 
about this person?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Don't you really know?  I assure you we're all 
so distressed about it.  Only last night at dear Lady Jansen's 
every one was saying how extraordinary it was that, of all men in 
London, Windermere should behave in such a way.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  My husband - what has HE got to do with any woman 
of that kind?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Ah, what indeed, dear?  That is the point.  He 
goes to see her continually, and stops for hours at a time, and 
while he is there she is not at home to any one.  Not that many 
ladies call on her, dear, but she has a great many disreputable men 
friends - my own brother particularly, as I told you - and that is 
what makes it so dreadful about Windermere.  We looked upon HIM as 
being such a model husband, but I am afraid there is no doubt about 
it.  My dear nieces - you know the Saville girls, don't you? - such 
nice domestic creatures - plain, dreadfully plain, but so good - 
well, they're always at the window doing fancy work, and making 
ugly things for the poor, which I think so useful of them in these 
dreadful socialistic days, and this terrible woman has taken a 
house in Curzon Street, right opposite them - such a respectable 
street, too!  I don't know what we're coming to!  And they tell me 
that Windermere goes there four and five times a week - they SEE 
him.  They can't help it - and although they never talk scandal, 
they - well, of course - they remark on it to every one.  And the 
worst of it all is that I have been told that this woman has got a 
great deal of money out of somebody, for it seems that she came to 
London six months ago without anything at all to speak of, and now 
she has this charming house in Mayfair, drives her ponies in the 
Park every afternoon and all - well, all - since she has known poor 
dear Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh, I can't believe it!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  But it's quite true, my dear.  The whole of 
London knows it.  That is why I felt it was better to come and talk 
to you, and advise you to take Windermere away at once to Homburg 
or to Aix, where he'll have something to amuse him, and where you 
can watch him all day long.  I assure you, my dear, that on several 
occasions after I was first married, I had to pretend to be very 
ill, and was obliged to drink the most unpleasant mineral waters, 
merely to get Berwick out of town.  He was so extremely 
susceptible.  Though I am bound to say he never gave away any large 
sums of money to anybody.  He is far too high-principled for that!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Interrupting.]</stagedir>  Duchess, Duchess, it's 
impossible!  <stagedir>[Rising and crossing stage to C.]</stagedir>  We are only married 
two years.  Our child is but six months old.  <stagedir>[Sits in chair R. of 
L. table.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Ah, the dear pretty baby!  How is the little 
darling?  Is it a boy or a girl?  I hope a girl - Ah, no, I 
remember it's a boy!  I'm so sorry.  Boys are so wicked.  My boy is 
excessively immoral.  You wouldn't believe at what hours he comes 
home.  And he's only left Oxford a few months - I really don't know 
what they teach them there.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Are ALL men bad?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Oh, all of them, my dear, all of them, without 
any exception.  And they never grow any better.  Men become old, 
but they never become good.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Windermere and I married for love.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Yes, we begin like that.  It was only 
Berwick's brutal and incessant threats of suicide that made me 
accept him at all, and before the year was out, he was running 
after all kinds of petticoats, every colour, every shape, every 
material.  In fact, before the honeymoon was over, I caught him 
winking at my maid, a most pretty, respectable girl.  I dismissed 
her at once without a character. - No, I remember I passed her on 
to my sister; poor dear Sir George is so short-sighted, I thought 
it wouldn't matter.  But it did, though - it was most unfortunate.  
<stagedir>[Rises.]</stagedir>  And now, my dear child, I must go, as we are dining out.  
And mind you don't take this little aberration of Windermere's too 
much to heart.  Just take him abroad, and he'll come back to you 
all right.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Come back to me?  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>   <stagedir>[L.C.]</stagedir>  Yes, dear, these wicked women get our 
husbands away from us, but they always come back, slightly damaged, 
of course.  And don't make scenes, men hate them!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It is very kind of you, Duchess, to come and tell 
me all this.  But I can't believe that my husband is untrue to me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Pretty child!  I was like that once.  Now I 
know that all men are monsters.  <stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE rings bell.]</stagedir>  The 
only thing to do is to feed the wretches well.  A good cook does 
wonders, and that I know you have.  My dear Margaret, you are not 
going to cry?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You needn't be afraid, Duchess, I never cry.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  That's quite right, dear.  Crying is the 
refuge of plain women but the ruin of pretty ones.  Agatha, 
darling!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Entering L.]</stagedir>  Yes, mamma.  <stagedir>[Stands back of table 
L.C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Come and bid good-bye to Lady Windermere, and 
thank her for your charming visit.  <stagedir>[Coming down again.]</stagedir>  And by 
the way, I must thank you for sending a card to Mr. Hopper - he's 
that rich young Australian people are taking such notice of just at 
present.  His father made a great fortune by selling some kind of 
food in circular tins - most palatable, I believe - I fancy it is 
the thing the servants always refuse to eat.  But the son is quite 
interesting.  I think he's attracted by dear Agatha's clever talk.  
Of course, we should be very sorry to lose her, but I think that a 
mother who doesn't part with a daughter every season has no real 
affection.  We're coming to-night, dear.  <stagedir>[PARKER opens C. doors.]</stagedir>  
And remember my advice, take the poor fellow out of town at once, 
it is the only thing to do.  Good-bye, once more; come, Agatha.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exeunt DUCHESS and LADY AGATHA C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How horrible!  I understand now what Lord 
Darlington meant by the imaginary instance of the couple not two 
years married.  Oh! it can't be true - she spoke of enormous sums 
of money paid to this woman.  I know where Arthur keeps his bank 
book - in one of the drawers of that desk.  I might find out by 
that.  I WILL find out.  <stagedir>[Opens drawer.]</stagedir>  No, it is some hideous 
mistake.  <stagedir>[Rises and goes C.]</stagedir>  Some silly scandal!  He loves ME!  
He loves ME!  But why should I not look?  I am his wife, I have a 
right to look!  <stagedir>[Returns to bureau, takes out book and examines it 
page by page, smiles and gives a sigh of relief.]</stagedir>  I knew it! there 
is not a word of truth in this stupid story.  <stagedir>[Puts book back in 
dranver.  As the does so, starts and takes out another book.]</stagedir>  A 
second book - private - locked!  <stagedir>[Tries to open it, but fails.  
Sees paper knife on bureau, and with it cuts cover from book.  
Begins to start at the first page.]</stagedir>  'Mrs. Erlynne - £600 - Mrs. 
Erlynne - £700 - Mrs. Erlynne - £400.'  Oh! it is true!  It is 
true!  How horrible!  <stagedir>[Throws book on floor.]</stagedir>  <stagedir>[Enter LORD 
WINDERMERE C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Well, dear, has the fan been sent home yet?  
<stagedir>[Going R.C.  Sees book.]</stagedir>  Margaret, you have cut open my bank book.  
You have no right to do such a thing!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You think it wrong that you are found out, don't 
you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I think it wrong that a wife should spy on her 
husband.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I did not spy on you.  I never knew of this 
woman's existence till half an hour ago.  Some one who pitied me 
was kind enough to tell me what every one in London knows already - 
your daily visits to Curzon Street, your mad infatuation, the 
monstrous sums of money you squander on this infamous woman!  
<stagedir>[Crossing L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret! don't talk like that of Mrs. Erlynne, 
you don't know how unjust it is!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Turning to him.]</stagedir>  You are very jealous of Mrs. 
Erlynne's honour.  I wish you had been as jealous of mine.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Your honour is untouched, Margaret.  You don't 
think for a moment that - <stagedir>[Puts book back into desk.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I think that you spend your money strangely.  
That is all.  Oh, don't imagine I mind about the money.  As far as 
I am concerned, you may squander everything we have.  But what I DO 
mind is that you who have loved me, you who have taught me to love 
you, should pass from the love that is given to the love that is 
bought.  Oh, it's horrible!  <stagedir>[Sits on sofa.]</stagedir>  And it is I who feel 
degraded! YOU don't feel anything.  I feel stained, utterly 
stained.  You can't realise how hideous the last six months seems 
to me now - every kiss you have given me is tainted in my memory.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Crossing to her.]</stagedir>  Don't say that, Margaret.  I 
never loved any one in the whole world but you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rises.]</stagedir>  Who is this woman, then?  Why do you 
take a house for her?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I did not take a house for her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You gave her the money to do it, which is the 
same thing.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, as far as I have known Mrs. Erlynne -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Is there a Mr. Erlynne - or is he a myth?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Her husband died many years ago.  She is alone in 
the world.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No relations?  <stagedir>[A pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  None.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Rather curious, isn't it?  <stagedir>[L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[L.C.]</stagedir>  Margaret, I was saying to you - and I beg 
you to listen to me - that as far as I have known Mrs. Erlynne, she 
has conducted herself well.  If years ago -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh!  <stagedir>[Crossing R.C.]</stagedir>  I don't want details about 
her life!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir>  I am not going to give you any details 
about her life.  I tell you simply this - Mrs. Erlynne was once 
honoured, loved, respected.  She was well born, she had position - 
she lost everything - threw it away, if you like.  That makes it 
all the more bitter.  Misfortunes one can endure - they come from 
outside, they are accidents.  But to suffer for one's own faults - 
ah! - there is the sting of life.  It was twenty years ago, too.  
She was little more than a girl then.  She had been a wife for even 
less time than you have.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am not interested in her - and - you should not 
mention this woman and me in the same breath.  It is an error of 
taste.  <stagedir>[Sitting R. at desk.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, you could save this woman.  She wants 
to get back into society, and she wants you to help her.  <stagedir>[Crossing 
to her.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Me!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How impertinent of her!  <stagedir>[A pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, I came to ask you a great favour, and I 
still ask it of you, though you have discovered what I had intended 
you should never have known that I have given Mrs. Erlynne a large 
sum of money.  I want you to send her an invitation for our party 
to-night.  <stagedir>[Standing L. of her.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You are mad!  <stagedir>[Rises.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I entreat you.  People may chatter about her, do 
chatter about her, of course, but they don't know anything definite 
against her.  She has been to several houses - not to houses where 
you would go, I admit, but still to houses where women who are in 
what is called Society nowadays do go.  That does not content her.  
She wants you to receive her once.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  As a triumph for her, I suppose?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No; but because she knows that you are a good 
woman - and that if she comes here once she will have a chance of a 
happier, a surer life than she has had.  She will make no further 
effort to know you.  Won't you help a woman who is trying to get 
back?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No!  If a woman really repents, she never wishes 
to return to the society that has made or seen her ruin.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I beg of you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Crossing to door R.]</stagedir>  I am going to dress for 
dinner, and don't mention the subject again this evening.  Arthur 
<stagedir>[going to him C.]</stagedir>, you fancy because I have no father or mother 
that I am alone in the world, and that you can treat me as you 
choose.  You are wrong, I have friends, many friends.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[L.C.]</stagedir>  Margaret, you are talking foolishly, 
recklessly.  I won't argue with you, but I insist upon your asking 
Mrs. Erlynne to-night.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.C.]</stagedir>  I shall do nothing of the kind.  
<stagedir>[Crossing L. C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You refuse?  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Absolutely!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Ah, Margaret, do this for my sake; it is her last 
chance.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  What has that to do with me?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How hard good women are!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How weak bad men are!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, none of us men may be good enough for 
the women we marry - that is quite true - but you don't imagine I 
would ever - oh, the suggestion is monstrous!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why should YOU be different from other men?  I am 
told that there is hardly a husband in London who does not waste 
his life over SOME shameful passion.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am not one of them.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am not sure of that!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You are sure in your heart.  But don't make chasm 
after chasm between us.  God knows the last few minutes have thrust 
us wide enough apart.  Sit down and write the card.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Nothing in the whole world would induce me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Crossing to bureau.]</stagedir>  Then I will!  <stagedir>[Rings 
electric bell, sits and writes card.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You are going to invite this woman?  <stagedir>[Crossing to 
him.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  <stagedir>[Pause.  Enter PARKER.]</stagedir>  Parker!</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Yes, my lord.  <stagedir>[Comes down L.C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Have this note sent to Mrs. Erlynne at No. 84A 
Curzon Street.  <stagedir>[Crossing to L.C. and giving note to PARKER.]</stagedir>  
There is no answer!</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Arthur, if that woman comes here, I shall insult 
her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, don't say that.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I mean it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Child, if you did such a thing, there's not a 
woman in London who wouldn't pity you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  There is not a GOOD woman in London who would not 
applaud me.  We have been too lax.  We must make an example.  I 
propose to begin to-night.  <stagedir>[Picking up fan.]</stagedir>  Yes, you gave me 
this fan to-day; it was your birthday present.  If that woman 
crosses my threshold, I shall strike her across the face with it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, you couldn't do such a thing.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You don't know me!  <stagedir>[Moves R.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER.]</stagedir>

Parker!</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Yes, my lady.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I shall dine in my own room.  I don't want 
dinner, in fact.  See that everything is ready by half-past ten.  
And, Parker, be sure you pronounce the names of the guests very 
distinctly to-night.  Sometimes you speak so fast that I miss them.  
I am particularly anxious to hear the names quite clearly, so as to 
make no mistake.  You understand, Parker?</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Yes, my lady.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  That will do!

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER C.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Speaking to LORD WINDERMERE]</stagedir>  Arthur, if that woman comes here - I 
warn you -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Margaret, you'll ruin us!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Us!  From this moment my life is sespeechte from 
yours.  But if you wish to avoid a public scandal, write at once to 
this woman, and tell her that I forbid her to come here!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I will not - I cannot - she must come!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Then I shall do exactly as I have said.  <stagedir>[Goes 
R.]</stagedir>  You leave me no choice.  <stagedir>[Exit R.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Calling after her.]</stagedir>  Margaret!  Margaret!  <stagedir>[A 
pause.]</stagedir>  My God!  What shall I do?  I dare not tell her who this 
woman really is.  The shame would kill her.  <stagedir>[Sinks down into a 
chair and buries his face in his hands.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>ACT DROP</stagedir>

</act>

<act>

<title>SECOND ACT</title>

<scndesc>SCENE
Drawing-room in Lord Windermere's house.  Door R.U. opening into 
ball-room, where band is playing.  Door L. through which guests are 
entering.  Door L.U. opens on to illuminated terrace.  Palms, 
flowers, and brilliant lights.  Room crowded with guests.  Lady 
Windermere is receiving them.</scndesc>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Up C.]</stagedir>  So strange Lord Windermere isn't 
here.  Mr. Hopper is very late, too.  You have kept those five 
dances for him, Agatha?  <stagedir>[Comes down.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Sitting on sofa.]</stagedir>  Just let me see your card.  
I'm so glad Lady Windermere has revived cards. - They're a mother's 
only safeguard.  You dear simple little thing!  <stagedir>[Scratches out two 
names.]</stagedir>  No nice girl should ever waltz with such particularly 
younger sons!  It looks so fast!  The last two dances you might 
pass on the terrace with Mr. Hopper.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter MR. DUMBY and LADY PLYMDALE from the ball-room.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Fanning herself.]</stagedir>  The air is so pleasant 
there.</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mrs. Cowper-Cowper.  Lady Stutfield.  Sir James Royston.  
Mr. Guy Berkeley.</speech>

<stagedir>[These people enter as announced.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Good evening, Lady Stutfield.  I suppose this will be the 
last ball of the season?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY STUTFIELD.</speaker>  I suppose so, Mr. Dumby.  It's been a delightful 
season, hasn't it?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Quite delightful!  Good evening, Duchess.  I suppose this 
will be the last ball of the season?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  I suppose so, Mr. Dumby.  It has been a very 
dull season, hasn't it?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Dreadfully dull!  Dreadfully dull!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MR. COWPER-COWPER.</speaker>  Good evening, Mr. Dumby.  I suppose this will 
be the last ball of the season?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Oh, I think not.  There'll probably be two more.  <stagedir>[Wanders 
back to LADY PLYMDALE.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mr. Rufford.  Lady Jedburgh and Miss Graham.  Mr. Hopper.</speech>

<stagedir>[These people enter as announced.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  How do you do, Lady Windermere?  How do you do, Duchess?  
<stagedir>[Bows to LADY AGATHA.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Dear Mr. Hopper, how nice of you to come so 
early.  We all know how you are run after in London.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  Capital place, London!  They are not nearly so exclusive 
in London as they are in Sydney.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Ah! we know your value, Mr. Hopper.  We wish 
there were more like you.  It would make life so much easier.  Do 
you know, Mr. Hopper, dear Agatha and I are so much interested in 
Australia.  It must be so pretty with all the dear little kangaroos 
flying about.  Agatha has found it on the map.  What a curious 
shape it is!  Just like a large packing case.  However, it is a 
very young country, isn't it?</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  Wasn't it made at the same time as the others, Duchess?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  How clever you are, Mr. Hopper.  You have a 
cleverness quite of your own.  Now I mustn't keep you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  But I should like to dance with Lady Agatha, Duchess.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Well, I hope she has a dance left.  Have you a 
dance left, Agatha?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  The next one?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  May I have the pleasure?  <stagedir>[LADY AGATHA bows.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Mind you take great care of my little 
chatterbox, Mr. Hopper.</speech>

<stagedir>[LADY AGATHA and MR. HOPPER pass into ball-room.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>

<speech>LORD WINDERMERE.  Margaret, I want to speak to you.</speech>

<speech>LADY WINDERMERE.  In a moment.  <stagedir>[The music drops.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Lord Augustus Lorton.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD AUGUSTUS.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Good evening, Lady Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Sir James, will you take me into the ball-
room?  Augustus has been dining with us to-night.  I really have 
had quite enough of dear Augustus for the moment.</speech>

<stagedir>[SIR JAMES ROYSTON gives the DUCHESS his aim and escorts her into 
the ball-room.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Bowden.  Lord and Lady Paisley.  Lord 
Darlington.</speech>

<stagedir>[These people enter as announced.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coming up to LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  Want to speak to 
you particularly, dear boy.  I'm worn to a shadow.  Know I don't 
look it.  None of us men do look what we really are.  Demmed good 
thing, too.  What I want to know is this.  Who is she?  Where does 
she come from?  Why hasn't she got any demmed relations?  Demmed 
nuisance, relations!  But they make one so demmed respectable.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You are talking of Mrs. Erlynne, I suppose?  I 
only met her six months ago.  Till then, I never knew of her 
existence.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  You have seen a good deal of her since then.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coldly.]</stagedir>  Yes, I have seen a good deal of her 
since then.  I have just seen her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Egad! the women are very down on her.  I have been 
dining with Arabella this evening!  By Jove! you should have heard 
what she said about Mrs. Erlynne.  She didn't leave a rag on her.  
. . <stagedir>[Aside.]</stagedir>  Berwick and I told her that didn't matter much, as 
the lady in question must have an extremely fine figure.  You 
should have seen Arabella's expression! . . . But, look here, dear 
boy.  I don't know what to do about Mrs. Erlynne.  Egad!  I might 
be married to her; she treats me with such demmed indifference.  
She's deuced clever, too!  She explains everything.  Egad! she 
explains you.  She has got any amount of explanations for you - and 
all of them different.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No explanations are necessary about my friendship 
with Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Hem!  Well, look here, dear old fellow.  Do you 
think she will ever get into this demmed thing called Society?  
Would you introduce her to your wife?  No use beating about the 
confounded bush.  Would you do that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne is coming here to-night.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Your wife has sent her a card?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne has received a card.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Then she's all right, dear boy.  But why didn't you 
tell me that before?  It would have saved me a heap of worry and 
demmed misunderstandings!</speech>

<stagedir>[LADY AGATHA and MR. HOPPER cross and exit on terrace L.U.E.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mr. Cecil Graham!</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter MR. CECIL GRAHAM.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Bows to LADY WINDERMERE, passes over and shakes 
hands with LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  Good evening, Arthur.  Why don't you 
ask me how I am?  I like people to ask me how I am.  It shows a 
wide-spread interest in my health.  Now, to-night I am not at all 
well.  Been dining with my people.  Wonder why it is one's people 
are always so tedious?  My father would talk morality after dinner.  
I told him he was old enough to know better.  But my experience is 
that as soon as people are old enough to know better, they don't 
know anything at all.  Hallo, Tuppy!  Hear you're going to be 
married again; thought you were tired of that game.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  You're excessively trivial, my dear boy, 
excessively trivial!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  By the way, Tuppy, which is it?  Have you been twice 
married and once divorced, or twice divorced and once married?  I 
say you've been twice divorced and once married.  It seems so much 
more probable.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  I have a very bad memory.  I really don't remember 
which.  <stagedir>[Moves away R.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  Lord Windermere, I've something most particular to 
ask you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am afraid - if you will excuse me - I must join 
my wife.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  Oh, you mustn't dream of such a thing.  It's most 
dangerous nowadays for a husband to pay any attention to his wife 
in public.  It always makes people think that he beats her when 
they're alone.  The world has grown so suspicious of anything that 
looks like a happy married life.  But I'll tell you what it is at 
supper.  <stagedir>[Moves towards door of ball-room.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir>  Margaret!  I MUST speak to you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Will you hold my fan for me, Lord Darlington?  
Thanks.  <stagedir>[Comes down to him.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Crossing to her.]</stagedir>  Margaret, what you said 
before dinner was, of course, impossible?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  That woman is not coming here to-night!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.C.]</stagedir>  Mrs. Erlynne is coming here, and if you 
in any way annoy or wound her, you will bring shame and sorrow on 
us both.  Remember that!  Ah, Margaret! only trust me!  A wife 
should trust her husband!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir>  London is full of women who trust their 
husbands.  One can always recognise them.  They look so thoroughly 
unhappy.  I am not going to be one of them.  <stagedir>[Moves up.]</stagedir>  Lord 
Darlington, will you give me back my fan, please?  Thanks. . . . A 
useful thing a fan, isn't it? . . . I want a friend to-night, Lord 
Darlington:  I didn't know I would want one so soon.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Lady Windermere!  I knew the time would come some 
day; but why to-night?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I WILL tell her.  I must.  It would be terrible 
if there were any scene.  Margaret . . .</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne!</speech>

<stagedir>[LORD WINDERMERE starts.  MRS. ERLYNNE enters, very beautifully 
dressed and very dignified.  LADY WINDERMERE clutches at her fan, 
then lets it drop on the door.  She bows coldly to MRS. ERLYNNE, 
who bows to her sweetly in turn, and sails into the room.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You have dropped your fan, Lady Windermere.  
<stagedir>[Picks it up and hands it to her.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir>  How do you do, again, Lord Windermere?  How 
charming your sweet wife looks!  Quite a picture!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[In a low voice.]</stagedir>  It was terribly rash of you to 
come!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  The wisest thing I ever did in my life.  
And, by the way, you must pay me a good deal of attention this 
evening.  I am afraid of the women.  You must introduce me to some 
of them.  The men I can always manage.  How do you do, Lord 
Augustus?  You have quite neglected me lately.  I have not seen you 
since yesterday.  I am afraid you're faithless.  Every one told me 
so.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.]</stagedir>  Now really, Mrs. Erlynne, allow me to 
explain.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.C.]</stagedir>  No, dear Lord Augustus, you can't explain 
anything.  It is your chief charm.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Ah! if you find charms in me, Mrs. Erlynne -</speech>

<stagedir>[They converse together.  LORD WINDERMERE moves uneasily about the 
room watching MRS. ERLYNNE.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[To LADY WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  How pale you are!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Cowards are always pale!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You look faint.  Come out on the terrace.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  <stagedir>[To PARKER.]</stagedir>  Parker, send my cloak out.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Crossing to her.]</stagedir>  Lady Windermere, how beautifully 
your terrace is illuminated.  Reminds me of Prince Doria's at Rome.

<stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE bows coldly, and goes off with LORD DARLINGTON.]</stagedir>

Oh, how do you do, Mr. Graham?  Isn't that your aunt, Lady 
Jedburgh?  I should so much like to know her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[After a moment's hesitation and embarrassment.]</stagedir>  
Oh, certainly, if you wish it.  Aunt Caroline, allow me to 
introduce Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  So pleased to meet you, Lady Jedburgh.  <stagedir>[Sits beside 
her on the sofa.]</stagedir>  Your nephew and I are great friends.  I am so 
much interested in his political career.  I think he's sure to be a 
wonderful success.  He thinks like a Tory, and talks like a 
Radical, and that's so important nowadays.  He's such a brilliant 
talker, too.  But we all know from whom he inherits that.  Lord 
Allandale was saying to me only yesterday, in the Park, that Mr. 
Graham talks almost as well as his aunt.</speech>

<speech>LADY JEDBURGH.  <stagedir>[R.]</stagedir>  Most kind of you to say these charming things 
to me!  <stagedir>[MRS.  ERLYNNE smiles, and continues conversation.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  <stagedir>[To CECIL GRAHAM.]</stagedir>  Did you introduce Mrs. Erlynne to Lady 
Jedburgh?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Had to, my dear fellow.  Couldn't help it!  That 
woman can make one do anything she wants.  How, I don't know.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Hope to goodness she won't speak to me!  <stagedir>[Saunters towards 
LADY PLYMDALE.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.  To LADY JEDBURGH.]</stagedir>  On Thursday?  With great 
pleasure.  <stagedir>[Rises, and speaks to LORD WINDERMERE, laughing.]</stagedir>  What 
a bore it is to have to be civil to these old dowagers!  But they 
always insist on it!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[To MR. DUMBY.]</stagedir>  Who is that well-dressed woman 
talking to Windermere?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Haven't got the slightest idea!  Looks like an EDITION DE 
LUXE of a wicked French novel, meant specially for the English 
market.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  So that is poor Dumby with Lady Plymdale?  I hear 
she is frightfully jealous of him.  He doesn't seem anxious to 
speak to me to-night.  I suppose he is afraid of her.  Those straw-
coloured women have dreadful tempers.  Do you know, I think I'll 
dance with you first, Windermere.  <stagedir>[LORD WINDERMERE bits his lip 
and frowns.]</stagedir>  It will make Lord Augustus so jealous!  Lord 
Augustus!  <stagedir>[LORD AUGUSTUS comes down.]</stagedir>  Lord Windermere insists on 
my dancing with him first, and, as it's his own house, I can't well 
refuse.  You know I would much sooner dance with you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a low bow.]</stagedir>  I wish I could think so, Mrs. 
Erlynne.</speech>

<speech>MRS ERLYNNE.  You know it far too well.  I can fancy a person 
dancing through life with you and finding it charming.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Placing his hand on his white waistcoat.]</stagedir>  Oh, 
thank you, thank you.  You are the most adorable of all ladies!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  What a nice speech!  So simple and so sincere!  Just 
the sort of speech I like.  Well, you shall hold my bouquet.  <stagedir>[Goes 
towards ball-room on LORD WINDERMERE'S arm.]</stagedir>  Ah, Mr. Dumby, how 
are you?  I am so sorry I have been out the last three times you 
have called.  Come and lunch on Friday.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With perfect nonchalance.]</stagedir>  Delighted!</speech>

<stagedir>[LADY PLYMDALE glares with indignation at MR. DUMBY.  LORD AUGUSTUS 
follows MRS. ERLYNNE and LORD WINDERMERE into the ball-room holding 
bouquet]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[To MR. DUMBY.]</stagedir>  What an absolute brute you are!  I 
never can believe a word you say!  Why did you tell me you didn't 
know her?  What do you mean by calling on her three times running?  
You are not to go to lunch there; of course you understand that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  My dear Laura, I wouldn't dream of going!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  You haven't told me her name yet!  Who is she?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coughs slightly and smooths his hair.]</stagedir>  She's a Mrs. 
Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  That woman!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Yes; that is what every one calls her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  How very interesting!  How intensely interesting!  
I really must have a good stare at her.  <stagedir>[Goes to door of ball-room 
and looks in.]</stagedir>  I have heard the most shocking things about her.  
They say she is ruining poor Windermere.  And Lady Windermere, who 
goes in for being so proper, invites her!  How extremely amusing!  
It takes a thoroughly good woman to do a thoroughly stupid thing.  
You are to lunch there on Friday!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Why?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  Because I want you to take my husband with you.  He 
has been so attentive lately, that he has become a perfect 
nuisance.  Now, this woman is just the thing for him.  He'll dance 
attendance upon her as long as she lets him, and won't bother me.  
I assure you, women of that kind are most useful.  They form the 
basis of other people's marriages.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  What a mystery you are!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Looking at him.]</stagedir>  I wish YOU were!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  I am - to myself.  I am the only person in the world I 
should like to know thoroughly; but I don't see any chance of it 
just at present.</speech>

<stagedir>[They pass into the ball-room, and LADY WINDERMERE and LORD 
DARLINGTON enter from the terrace.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  Her coming here is monstrous, unbearable.  
I know now what you meant to-day at tea-time.  Why didn't you tell 
me right out?  You should have!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I couldn't!  A man can't tell these things about 
another man!  But if I had known he was going to make you ask her 
here to-night, I think I would have told you.  That insult, at any 
rate, you would have been spared.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I did not ask her.  He insisted on her coming - 
against my entreaties - against my commands.  Oh! the house is 
tainted for me!  I feel that every woman here sneers at me as she 
dances by with my husband.  What have I done to deserve this?  I 
gave him all my life.  He took it - used it - spoiled it!  I am 
degraded in my own eyes; and I lack courage - I am a coward!  <stagedir>[Sits 
down on sofa.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  If I know you at all, I know that you can't live 
with a man who treats you like this!  What sort of life would you 
have with him?  You would feel that he was lying to you every 
moment of the day.  You would feel that the look in his eyes was 
false, his voice false, his touch false, his passion false.  He 
would come to you when he was weary of others; you would have to 
comfort him.  He would come to you when he was devoted to others; 
you would have to charm him.  You would have to be to him the mask 
of his real life, the cloak to hide his secret.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You are right - you are terribly right.  But 
where am I to turn?  You said you would be my friend, Lord 
Darlington. - Tell me, what am I to do?  Be my friend now.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Between men and women there is no friendship 
possible.  There is passion, enmity, worship, love, but no 
friendship.  I love you -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No, no!  <stagedir>[Rises.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Yes, I love you!  You are more to me than 
anything in the whole world.  What does your husband give you?  
Nothing.  Whatever is in him he gives to this wretched woman, whom 
he has thrust into your society, into your home, to shame you 
before every one.  I offer you my life -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Lord Darlington!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  My life - my whole life.  Take it, and do with it 
what you will. . . . I love you - love you as I have never loved 
any living thing.  From the moment I met you I loved you, loved you 
blindly, adoringly, madly!  You did not know it then - you know it 
now!  Leave this house to-night.  I won't tell you that the world 
matters nothing, or the world's voice, or the voice of society.  
They matter a great deal.  They matter far too much.  But there are 
moments when one has to choose between living one's own life, 
fully, entirely, completely - or dragging out some false, shallow, 
degrading existence that the world in its hypocrisy demands.  You 
have that moment now.  Choose!  Oh, my love, choose.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Moving slowly away from him, and looking at him 
with startled eyes.]</stagedir>  I have not the courage.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Following her.]</stagedir>  Yes; you have the courage.  
There may be six months of pain, of disgrace even, but when you no 
longer bear his name, when you bear mine, all will be well.  
Margaret, my love, my wife that shall be some day - yes, my wife!  
You know it!  What are you now?  This woman has the place that 
belongs by right to you.  Oh! go - go out of this house, with head 
erect, with a smile upon your lips, with courage in your eyes.  All 
London will know why you did it; and who will blame you?  No one.  
If they do, what matter?  Wrong?  What is wrong?  It's wrong for a 
man to abandon his wife for a shameless woman.  It is wrong for a 
wife to remain with a man who so dishonours her.  You said once you 
would make no compromise with things.  Make none now.  Be brave!  
Be yourself!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am afraid of being myself.  Let me think!  Let 
me wait!  My husband may return to me.  <stagedir>[Sits down on sofa.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  And you would take him back!  You are not what I 
thought you were.  You are just the same as every other woman.  You 
would stand anything rather than face the censure of a world, whose 
praise you would despise.  In a week you will be driving with this 
woman in the Park.  She will be your constant guest - your dearest 
friend.  You would endure anything rather than break with one blow 
this monstrous tie.  You are right.  You have no courage; none!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Ah, give me time to think.  I cannot answer you 
now.  <stagedir>[Passes her hand nervously over her brow.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  It must be now or not at all.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising from the sofa.]</stagedir>  Then, not at all!  <stagedir>[A 
pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You break my heart!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Mine is already broken.  <stagedir>[A pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  To-morrow I leave England.  This is the last time 
I shall ever look on you.  You will never see me again.  For one 
moment our lives met - our souls touched.  They must never meet or 
touch again.  Good-bye, Margaret.  <stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How alone I am in life!  How terribly alone!</speech>

<stagedir>[The music stops.  Enter the DUCHESS OF BERWICK and LORD PAISLEY 
laughing and talking.  Other guests come on from ball-room.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Dear Margaret, I've just been having such a 
delightful chat with Mrs. Erlynne.  I am so sorry for what I said 
to you this afternoon about her.  Of course, she must be all right 
if YOU invite her.  A most attractive woman, and has such sensible 
views on life.  Told me she entirely disapproved of people marrying 
more than once, so I feel quite safe about poor Augustus.  Can't 
imagine why people speak against her.  It's those horrid nieces of 
mine - the Saville girls - they're always talking scandal.  Still, 
I should go to Homburg, dear, I really should.  She is just a 
little too attractive.  But where is Agatha?  Oh, there she is:   
<stagedir>[LADY AGATHA and MR. HOPPER enter from terrace L.U.E.]</stagedir>  Mr. Hopper, 
I am very, very angry with you.  You have taken Agatha out on the 
terrace, and she is so delicate.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  Awfully sorry, Duchess.  We went out for a moment and then 
got chatting together.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir>  Ah, about dear Australia, I suppose?</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  Yes!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Agatha, darling!  <stagedir>[Beckons her over.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Aside.]</stagedir>  Did Mr. Hopper definitely -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  And what answer did you give him, dear child?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Affectionately.]</stagedir>  My dear one!  You always 
say the right thing.  Mr. Hopper!  James!  Agatha has told me 
everything.  How cleverly you have both kept your secret.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  You don't mind my taking Agatha off to Australia, then, 
Duchess?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Indignantly.]</stagedir>  To Australia?  Oh, don't 
mention that dreadful vulgar place.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  But she said she'd like to come with me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Severely.]</stagedir>  Did you say that, Agatha?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY AGATHA.</speaker>  Yes, mamma.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  Agatha, you say the most silly things 
possible.  I think on the whole that Grosvenor Square would be a 
more healthy place to reside in.  There are lots of vulgar people 
live in Grosvenor Square, but at any rate there are no horrid 
kangaroos crawling about.  But we'll talk about that to-morrow.  
James, you can take Agatha down.  You'll come to lunch, of course, 
James.  At half-past one, instead of two.  The Duke will wish to 
say a few words to you, I am sure.</speech>

<speech><speaker>HOPPER.</speaker>  I should like to have a chat with the Duke, Duchess.  He 
has not said a single word to me yet.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUCHESS OF BERWICK.</speaker>  I think you'll find he will have a great deal 
to say to you to-morrow.  <stagedir>[Exit LADY AGATHA with MR. HOPPER.]</stagedir>  And 
now good-night, Margaret.  I'm afraid it's the old, old story, 
dear.  Love - well, not love at first sight, but love at the end of 
the season, which is so much more satisfactory.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Good-night, Duchess.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit the DUCHESS OF BERWICK on LORD PAISLEY'S arm.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  My dear Margaret, what a handsome woman your 
husband has been dancing with!  I should be quite jealous if I were 
you!  Is she a great friend of yours?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY PLYMDALE.</speaker>  Really?  Good-night, dear.  <stagedir>[Looks at MR. DUMBY and 
exit.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Awful manners young Hopper has!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Ah!  Hopper is one of Nature's gentlemen, the worst 
type of gentleman I know.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Sensible woman, Lady Windermere.  Lots of wives would have 
objected to Mrs. Erlynne coming.  But Lady Windermere has that 
uncommon thing called common sense.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  And Windermere knows that nothing looks so like 
innocence as an indiscretion.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Yes; dear Windermere is becoming almost modern.  Never 
thought he would.  <stagedir>[Bows to LADY WINDERMERE and exit.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY JEDBURGH.</speaker>  Good night, Lady Windermere.  What a fascinating 
woman Mrs. Erlynne is!  She is coming to lunch on Thursday, won't 
you come too?  I expect the Bishop and dear Lady Merton.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am afraid I am engaged, Lady Jedburgh.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY JEDBURGH.</speaker>  So sorry.  Come, dear.  <stagedir>[Exeunt LADY JEDBURGH and 
MISS GRAHAM.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>[Enter MRS. ERLYNNE and LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Charming ball it has been!  Quite reminds me of old 
days.  <stagedir>[Sits on sofa.]</stagedir>  And I see that there are just as many fools 
in society as there used to be.  So pleased to find that nothing 
has altered!  Except Margaret.  She's grown quite pretty.  The last 
time I saw her - twenty years ago, she was a fright in flannel.  
Positive fright, I assure you.  The dear Duchess! and that sweet 
Lady Agatha!  Just the type of girl I like!  Well, really, 
Windermere, if I am to be the Duchess's sister-in-law</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Sitting L. of her.]</stagedir>  But are you - ?</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit MR. CECIL GRAHAM with rest of guests.  LADY WINDERMERE 
watches, with a look of scorn and pain, MRS. ERLYNNE and her 
husband.  They are unconscious of her presence.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh, yes!  He's to call to-morrow at twelve o'clock!  
He wanted to propose to-night.  In fact he did.  He kept on 
proposing.  Poor Augustus, you know how he repeats himself.  Such a 
bad habit!  But I told him I wouldn't give him an answer till to-
morrow.  Of course I am going to take him.  And I dare say I'll 
make him an admirable wife, as wives go.  And there is a great deal 
of good in Lord Augustus.  Fortunately it is all on the surface.  
Just where good qualities should be.  Of course you must help me in 
this matter.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am not called on to encourage Lord Augustus, I 
suppose?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh, no!  I do the encouraging.  But you will make me 
a handsome settlement, Windermere, won't you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Frowning.]</stagedir>  Is that what you want to talk to me 
about to-night?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a gesture of impatience.]</stagedir>  I will not talk 
of it here.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Laughing.]</stagedir>  Then we will talk of it on the terrace.  
Even business should have a picturesque background.  Should it not, 
Windermere?  With a proper background women can do anything.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Won't to-morrow do as well?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  No; you see, to-morrow I am going to accept him.  
And I think it would be a good thing if I was able to tell him that 
I had - well, what shall I say? - £2000 a year left to me by a 
third cousin - or a second husband - or some distant relative of 
that kind.  It would be an additional attraction, wouldn't it?  You 
have a delightful opportunity now of paying me a compliment, 
Windermere.  But you are not very clever at paying compliments.  I 
am afraid Margaret doesn't encourage you in that excellent habit.  
It's a great mistake on her part.  When men give up saying what is 
charming, they give up thinking what is charming.  But seriously, 
what do you say to £2000?  £2500, I think.  In modern life margin 
is everything.  Windermere, don't you think the world an intensely 
amusing place?  I do!</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit on terrace with LORD WINDERMERE.  Music strikes up in ball-
room.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  To stay in this house any longer is impossible.  
To-night a man who loves me offered me his whole life.  I refused 
it.  It was foolish of me.  I will offer him mine now.  I will give 
him mine.  I will go to him!  <stagedir>[Puts on cloak and goes to the door, 
then turns back.  Sits down at table and writes a letter, puts it 
into an envelope, and leaves it on table.]</stagedir>  Arthur has never 
understood me.  When he reads this, he will.  He may do as he 
chooses now with his life.  I have done with mine as I think best, 
as I think right.  It is he who has broken the bond of marriage - 
not I.  I only break its bondage.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[PARKER enters L. and crosses towards the ball-room R.  Enter MRS. 
ERLYNNE.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Is Lady Windermere in the ball-room?</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Her ladyship has just gone out.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Gone out?  She's not on the terrace?</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  No, madam.  Her ladyship has just gone out of the house.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Starts, and looks at the servant with a puzzled 
expression in her face.]</stagedir>  Out of the house?</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Yes, madam - her ladyship told me she had left a letter 
for his lordship on the table.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  A letter for Lord Windermere?</speech>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Yes, madam.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Thank you.

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER.  The music in the ball-room stops.]</stagedir>  Gone out of her 
house!  A letter addressed to her husband!  <stagedir>[Goes over to bureau 
and looks at letter.  Takes it up and lays it down again with a 
shudder of fear.]</stagedir>  No, no!  It would be impossible!  Life doesn't 
repeat its tragedies like that!  Oh, why does this horrible fancy 
come across me?  Why do I remember now the one moment of my life I 
most wish to forget?  Does life repeat its tragedies?  <stagedir>[Tears 
letter open and reads it, then sinks down into a chair with a 
gesture of anguish.]</stagedir>  Oh, how terrible!  The same words that twenty 
years ago I wrote to her father! and how bitterly I have been 
punished for it!  No; my punishment, my real punishment is to-
night, is now!  <stagedir>[Still seated R.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD WINDERMERE L.U.E.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Have you said good-night to my wife?  <stagedir>[Comes C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Crushing letter in her hand.]</stagedir>  Yes.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Where is she?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  She is very tired.  She has gone to bed.  She said 
she had a headache.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I must go to her.  You'll excuse me?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising hurriedly.]</stagedir>  Oh, no!  It's nothing serious.  
She's only very tired, that is all.  Besides, there are people 
still in the supper-room.  She wants you to make her apologies to 
them.  She said she didn't wish to be disturbed.  <stagedir>[Drops letter.]</stagedir>  
She asked me to tell you!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Picks up letter.]</stagedir>  You have dropped something.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh yes, thank you, that is mine.  <stagedir>[Puts out her hand 
to take it.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Still looking at letter.]</stagedir>  But it's my wife's 
handwriting, isn't it?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Takes the letter quickly.]</stagedir>  Yes, it's - an address.  
Will you ask them to call my carriage, please?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Certainly.</speech>

<stagedir>[Goes L. and Exit.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Thanks!  What can I do?  What can I do?  I feel a 
passion awakening within me that I never felt before.  What can it 
mean?  The daughter must not be like the mother - that would be 
terrible.  How can I save her?  How can I save my child?  A moment 
may ruin a life.  Who knows that better than I?  Windermere must be 
got out of the house; that is absolutely necessary.  <stagedir>[Goes L.]</stagedir>  But 
how shall I do it?  It must be done somehow.  Ah!</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD AUGUSTUS R.U.E. carrying bouquet.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Dear lady, I am in such suspense!  May I not have 
an answer to my request?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Lord Augustus, listen to me.  You are to take Lord 
Windermere down to your club at once, and keep him there as long as 
possible.  You understand?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  But you said you wished me to keep early hours!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Nervously.]</stagedir>  Do what I tell you.  Do what I tell 
you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  And my reward?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Your reward?  Your reward?  Oh! ask me that to-
morrow.  But don't let Windermere out of your sight to-night.  If 
you do I will never forgive you.  I will never speak to you again.  
I'll have nothing to do with you.  Remember you are to keep 
Windermere at your club, and don't let him come back to-night.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit L.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Well, really, I might be her husband already.  
Positively I might.  <stagedir>[Follows her in a bewildered manner.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>ACT DROP.</stagedir>

</act>

<act>

<title>THIRD ACT</title>

<scndesc>SCENE
Lord Darlington's Rooms.  A large sofa is in front of fireplace R.  
At the back of the stage a curtain is drawn across the window.  
Doors L. and R.  Table R. with writing materials.  Table C. with 
syphons, glasses, and Tantalus frame.  Table L. with cigar and 
cigarette box.  Lamps lit.</scndesc>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Standing by the fireplace.]</stagedir>  Why doesn't he 
come?  This waiting is horrible.  He should be here.  Why is he not 
here, to wake by passionate words some fire within me?  I am cold - 
cold as a loveless thing.  Arthur must have read my letter by this 
time.  If he cared for me, he would have come after me, would have 
taken me back by force.  But he doesn't care.  He's entrammelled by 
this woman - fascinated by her - dominated by her.  If a woman 
wants to hold a man, she has merely to appeal to what is worst in 
him.  We make gods of men and they leave us.  Others make brutes of 
them and they fawn and are faithful.  How hideous life is! . . . 
Oh! it was mad of me to come here, horribly mad.  And yet, which is 
the worst, I wonder, to be at the mercy of a man who loves one, or 
the wife of a man who in one's own house dishonours one?  What 
woman knows?  What woman in the whole world?  But will he love me 
always, this man to whom I am giving my life?  What do I bring him?  
Lips that have lost the note of joy, eyes that are blinded by 
tears, chill hands and icy heart.  I bring him nothing.  I must go 
back - no; I can't go back, my letter has put me in their power - 
Arthur would not take me back!  That fatal letter!  No!  Lord 
Darlington leaves England to-morrow.  I will go with him - I have 
no choice.  <stagedir>[Sits down for a few moments.  Then starts up and puts 
on her cloak.]</stagedir>  No, no!  I will go back, let Arthur do with me what 
he pleases.  I can't wait here.  It has been madness my coming.  I 
must go at once.  As for Lord Darlington - Oh! here he is!  What 
shall I do?  What can I say to him?  Will he let me go away at all?  
I have heard that men are brutal, horrible . . . Oh!  <stagedir>[Hides her 
face in her hands.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>[Enter MRS. ERLYNNE L.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Lady Windermere!  <stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE starts and looks 
up.  Then recoils in contempt.]</stagedir>  Thank Heaven I am in time.  You 
must go back to your husband's house immediately.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Must?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Authoritatively.]</stagedir>  Yes, you must!  There is not a 
second to be lost.  Lord Darlington may return at any moment.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Don't come near me!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh!  You are on the brink of ruin, you are on the 
brink of a hideous precipice.  You must leave this place at once, 
my carriage is waiting at the corner of the street.  You must come 
with me and drive straight home.

<stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE throws off her cloak and flings it on the sofa.]</stagedir>

What are you doing?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne - if you had not come here, I would 
have gone back.  But now that I see you, I feel that nothing in the 
whole world would induce me to live under the same roof as Lord 
Windermere.  You fill me with horror.  There is something about you 
that stirs the wildest - rage within me.  And I know why you are 
here.  My husband sent you to lure me back that I might serve as a 
blind to whatever relations exist between you and him.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh!  You don't think that - you can't.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Go back to my husband, Mrs. Erlynne.  He belongs 
to you and not to me.  I suppose he is afraid of a scandal.  Men 
are such cowards.  They outrage every law of the world, and are 
afraid of the world's tongue.  But he had better prepare himself.  
He shall have a scandal.  He shall have the worst scandal there has 
been in London for years.  He shall see his name in every vile 
paper, mine on every hideous placard.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  No - no -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes! he shall.  Had he come himself, I admit I 
would have gone back to the life of degradation you and he had 
prepared for me - I was going back - but to stay himself at home, 
and to send you as his messenger - oh! it was infamous - infamous.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[C.]</stagedir>  Lady Windermere, you wrong me horribly - you 
wrong your husband horribly.  He doesn't know you are here - he 
thinks you are safe in your own house.  He thinks you are asleep in 
your own room.  He never read the mad letter you wrote to him!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.]</stagedir>  Never read it!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  No - he knows nothing about it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  How simple you think me!  <stagedir>[Going to her.]</stagedir>  You 
are lying to me!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Restraining herself.]</stagedir>  I am not.  I am telling you 
the truth.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  If my husband didn't read my letter, how is it 
that you are here?  Who told you I had left the house you were 
shameless enough to enter?  Who told you where I had gone to?  My 
husband told you, and sent you to decoy me back.  <stagedir>[Crosses L.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[R.C.]</stagedir>  Your husband has never seen the letter.  I - 
saw it, I opened it.  I - read it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Turning to her.]</stagedir>  You opened a letter of mine to 
my husband?  You wouldn't dare!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Dare!  Oh! to save you from the abyss into which you 
are falling, there is nothing in the world I would not dare, 
nothing in the whole world.  Here is the letter.  Your husband has 
never read it.  He never shall read it.  <stagedir>[Going to fireplace.]</stagedir>  It 
should never have been written.  <stagedir>[Tears it and throws it into the 
fire.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With infinite contempt in her voice and look.]</stagedir>  
How do I know that that was my letter after all?  You seem to think 
the commonest device can take me in!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh! why do you disbelieve everything I tell you?  
What object do you think I have in coming here, except to save you 
from utter ruin, to save you from the consequence of a hideous 
mistake?  That letter that is burnt now WAS your letter.  I swear 
it to you!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Slowly.]</stagedir>  You took good care to burn it before I 
had examined it.  I cannot trust you.  You, whose whole life is a 
lie, could you speak the truth about anything?  <stagedir>[Sits down.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Hurriedly.]</stagedir>  Think as you like about me - say what 
you choose against me, but go back, go back to the husband you 
love.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Sullenly.]</stagedir>  I do NOT love him!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  You do, and you know that he loves you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  He does not understand what love is.  He 
understands it as little as you do - but I see what you want.  It 
would be a great advantage for you to get me back.  Dear Heaven! 
what a life I would have then!  Living at the mercy of a woman who 
has neither mercy nor pity in her, a woman whom it is an infamy to 
meet, a degradation to know, a vile woman, a woman who comes 
between husband and wife!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a gesture of despair.]</stagedir>  Lady Windermere, Lady 
Windermere, don't say such terrible things.  You don't know how 
terrible they are, how terrible and how unjust.  Listen, you must 
listen!  Only go back to your husband, and I promise you never to 
communicate with him again on any pretext - never to see him - 
never to have anything to do with his life or yours.  The money 
that he gave me, he gave me not through love, but through hatred, 
not in worship, but in contempt.  The hold I have over him -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  Ah! you admit you have a hold!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes, and I will tell you what it is.  It is his love 
for you, Lady Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You expect me to believe that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  You must believe it!  It is true.  It is his love 
for you that has made him submit to - oh! call it what you like, 
tyranny, threats, anything you choose.  But it is his love for you.  
His desire to spare you - shame, yes, shame and disgrace.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  What do you mean?  You are insolent!  What have I 
to do with you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Humbly.]</stagedir>  Nothing.  I know it - but I tell you that 
your husband loves you - that you may never meet with such love 
again in your whole life - that such love you will never meet - and 
that if you throw it away, the day may come when you will starve 
for love and it will not be given to you, beg for love and it will 
be denied you - Oh! Arthur loves you!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Arthur?  And you tell me there is nothing between 
you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Lady Windermere, before Heaven your husband is 
guiltless of all offence towards you!  And I - I tell you that had 
it ever occurred to me that such a monstrous suspicion would have 
entered your mind, I would have died rather than have crossed your 
life or his - oh! died, gladly died!  <stagedir>[Moves away to sofa R.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You talk as if you had a heart.  Women like you 
have no hearts.  Heart is not in you.  You are bought and sold.  
<stagedir>[Sits L.C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Starts, with a gesture of pain.  Then restrains 
herself, and comes over to where LADY WINDERMERE is sitting.  As 
she speaks, she stretches out her hands towards her, but does not 
dare to touch her.]</stagedir>  Believe what you choose about me.  I am not 
worth a moment's sorrow.  But don't spoil your beautiful young life 
on my account!  You don't know what may be in store for you, unless 
you leave this house at once.  You don't know what it is to fall 
into the pit, to be despised, mocked, abandoned, sneered at - to be 
an outcast! to find the door shut against one, to have to creep in 
by hideous byways, afraid every moment lest the mask should be 
stripped from one's face, and all the while to hear the laughter, 
the horrible laughter of the world, a thing more tragic than all 
the tears the world has ever shed.  You don't know what it is.  One 
pays for one's sin, and then one pays again, and all one's life one 
pays.  You must never know that. - As for me, if suffering be an 
expiation, then at this moment I have expiated all my faults, 
whatever they have been; for to-night you have made a heart in one 
who had it not, made it and broken it. - But let that pass.  I may 
have wrecked my own life, but I will not let you wreck yours.  You 
- why, you are a mere girl, you would be lost.  You haven't got the 
kind of brains that enables a woman to get back.  You have neither 
the wit nor the courage.  You couldn't stand dishonour!  No!  Go 
back, Lady Windermere, to the husband who loves you, whom you love.  
You have a child, Lady Windermere.  Go back to that child who even 
now, in pain or in joy, may be calling to you.  <stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE 
rises.]</stagedir>  God gave you that child.  He will require from you that 
you make his life fine, that you watch over him.  What answer will 
you make to God if his life is ruined through you?  Back to your 
house, Lady Windermere - your husband loves you!  He has never 
swerved for a moment from the love he bears you.  But even if he 
had a thousand loves, you must stay with your child.  If he was 
harsh to you, you must stay with your child.  If he ill-treated 
you, you must stay with your child.  If he abandoned you, your 
place is with your child.

<stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE bursts into tears and buries her face in her 
hands.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Rushing to her.]</stagedir>  Lady Windermere!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Holding out her hands to her, helplessly, as a 
child might do.]</stagedir>  Take me home.  Take me home.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Is about to embrace her.  Then restrains herself.  
There is a look of wonderful joy in her face.]</stagedir>  Come!  Where is 
your cloak?  <stagedir>[Getting it from sofa.]</stagedir>  Here.  Put it on.  Come at 
once!</speech>

<stagedir>[They go to the door.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Stop!  Don't you hear voices?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  No, no!  There was no one!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, there is!  Listen!  Oh! that is my husband's 
voice!  He is coming in!  Save me!  Oh, it's some plot!  You have 
sent for him.</speech>

<stagedir>[Voices outside.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Silence!  I'm here to save you, if I can.  But I 
fear it is too late!  There! <stagedir>[Points to the curtain across the 
window.]</stagedir>  The first chance you have, slip out, if you ever get a 
chance!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  But you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh! never mind me.  I'll face them.</speech>

<stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE hides herself behind the curtain.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Outside.]</stagedir>  Nonsense, dear Windermere, you must not 
leave me!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Lord Augustus!  Then it is I who am lost!  
<stagedir>[Hesitates for a moment, then looks round and sees door R., and 
exits through it.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD DARLINGTON, MR. DUMBY, LORD WINDERMERE, LORD AUGUSTUS 
LORTON, and MR. CECIL GRAHAM.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  What a nuisance their turning us out of the club at this 
hour!  It's only two o'clock.  <stagedir>[Sinks into a chair.]</stagedir>  The lively 
part of the evening is only just beginning.  <stagedir>[Yawns and closes his 
eyes.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It is very good of you, Lord Darlington, allowing 
Augustus to force our company on you, but I'm afraid I can't stay 
long.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Really!  I am so sorry!  You'll take a cigar, 
won't you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Thanks!  <stagedir>[Sits down.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[To LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  My dear boy, you must not 
dream of going.  I have a great deal to talk to you about, of 
demmed importance, too.  <stagedir>[Sits down with him at L. table.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Oh!  We all know what that is!  Tuppy can't talk 
about anything but Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Well, that is no business of yours, is it, Cecil?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  None!  That is why it interests me.  My own business 
always bores me to death.  I prefer other people's.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Have something to drink, you fellows.  Cecil, 
you'll have a whisky and soda?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Thanks.  <stagedir>[Goes to table with LORD DARLINGTON.]</stagedir>  Mrs. 
Erlynne looked very handsome to-night, didn't she?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  I am not one of her admirers.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  I usen't to be, but I am now.  Why! she actually 
made me introduce her to poor dear Aunt Caroline.  I believe she is 
going to lunch there.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[In Purple.]</stagedir>  No?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  She is, really.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Excuse me, you fellows.  I'm going away to-
morrow.  And I have to write a few letters.  <stagedir>[Goes to writing table 
and sits down.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Clever woman, Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Hallo, Dumby!  I thought you were asleep.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  I am, I usually am!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  A very clever woman.  Knows perfectly well what a 
demmed fool I am - knows it as well as I do myself.

<stagedir>[CECIL GRAHAM comes towards him laughing.]</stagedir>

Ah, you may laugh, my boy, but it is a great thing to come across a 
woman who thoroughly understands one.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  It is an awfully dangerous thing.  They always end by 
marrying one.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  But I thought, Tuppy, you were never going to see 
her again!  Yes! you told me so yesterday evening at the club.  You 
said you'd heard -

<stagedir>[Whispering to him.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Oh, she's explained that.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  And the Wiesbaden affair?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  She's explained that too.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  And her income, Tuppy?  Has she explained that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[In a very serious voice.]</stagedir>  She's going to explain 
that to-morrow.</speech>

<stagedir>[CECIL GRAHAM goes back to C. table.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Awfully commercial, women nowadays.  Our grandmothers threw 
their caps over the mills, of course, but, by Jove, their 
granddaughters only throw their caps over mills that can raise the 
wind for them.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  You want to make her out a wicked woman.  She is 
not!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Oh!  Wicked women bother one.  Good women bore one.  
That is the only difference between them.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Puffing a cigar.]</stagedir>  Mrs. Erlynne has a future 
before her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne has a past before her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  I prefer women with a past.  They're always so 
demmed amusing to talk to.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Well, you'll have lots of topics of conversation 
with HER, Tuppy.  <stagedir>[Rising and going to him.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  You're getting annoying, dear-boy; you're getting 
demmed annoying.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Puts his hands on his shoulders.]</stagedir>  Now, Tuppy, 
you've lost your figure and you've lost your character.  Don't lose 
your temper; you have only got one.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  My dear boy, if I wasn't the most good-natured man 
in London -</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  We'd treat you with more respect, wouldn't we, 
Tuppy?  <stagedir>[Strolls away.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  The youth of the present day are quite monstrous.  They 
have absolutely no respect for dyed hair.  <stagedir>[LORD AUGUSTUS looks 
round angrily.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne has a very great respect for dear 
Tuppy.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Then Mrs. Erlynne sets an admirable example to the rest of 
her sex.  It is perfectly brutal the way most women nowadays behave 
to men who are not their husbands.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Dumby, you are ridiculous, and Cecil, you let 
your tongue run away with you.  You must leave Mrs. Erlynne alone.  
You don't really know anything about her, and you're always talking 
scandal against her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coming towards him L.C.]</stagedir>  My dear Arthur, I never 
talk scandal.  I only talk gossip.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  What is the difference between scandal and 
gossip?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Oh! gossip is charming!  History is merely gossip.  
But scandal is gossip made tedious by morality.  Now, I never 
moralise.  A man who moralises is usually a hypocrite, and a woman 
who moralises is invariably plain.  There is nothing in the whole 
world so unbecoming to a woman as a Nonconformist conscience.  And 
most women know it, I'm glad to say.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Just my sentiments, dear boy, just my sentiments.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Sorry to hear it, Tuppy; whenever people agree with 
me, I always feel I must be wrong.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  My dear boy, when I was your age -</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  But you never were, Tuppy, and you never will be.  
<stagedir>[Goes up C.]</stagedir>  I say, Darlington, let us have some cards.  You'll 
play, Arthur, won't you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No, thanks, Cecil.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a sigh.]</stagedir>  Good heavens! how marriage ruins a man!  
It's as demoralising as cigarettes, and far more expensive.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  You'll play, of course, Tuppy?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Pouring himself out a brandy and soda at table.]</stagedir>  
Can't, dear boy.  Promised Mrs. Erlynne never to play or drink 
again.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Now, my dear Tuppy, don't be led astray into the 
paths of virtue.  Reformed, you would be perfectly tedious.  That 
is the worst of women.  They always want one to be good.  And if we 
are good, when they meet us, they don't love us at all.  They like 
to find us quite irretrievably bad, and to leave us quite 
unattractively good.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising from R. table, where he has been writing 
letters.]</stagedir>  They always do find us bad!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  I don't think we are bad.  I think we are all good, except 
Tuppy.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  No, we are all in the gutter, but some of us are 
looking at the stars.  <stagedir>[Sits down at C. table.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  We are all in the gutter, but some of us are looking at the 
stars?  Upon my word, you are very romantic to-night, Darlington.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Too romantic!  You must be in love.  Who is the 
girl?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  The woman I love is not free, or thinks she 
isn't.  <stagedir>[Glances instinctively at LORD WINDERMERE while he speaks.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  A married woman, then!  Well, there's nothing in the 
world like the devotion of a married woman.  It's a thing no 
married man knows anything about.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Oh! she doesn't love me.  She is a good woman.  
She is the only good woman I have ever met in my life.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  The only good woman you have ever met in your life?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Yes!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Lighting a cigarette.]</stagedir>  Well, you are a lucky 
fellow!  Why, I have met hundreds of good women.  I never seem to 
meet any but good women.  The world is perfectly packed with good 
women.  To know them is a middle-class education.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  This woman has purity and innocence.  She has 
everything we men have lost.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  My dear fellow, what on earth should we men do going 
about with purity and innocence?  A carefully thought-out 
buttonhole is much more effective.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  She doesn't really love you then?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  No, she does not!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  I congratulate you, my dear fellow.  In this world there 
are only two tragedies.  One is not getting what one wants, and the 
other is getting it.  The last is much the worst; the last is a 
real tragedy!  But I am interested to hear she does not love you.  
How long could you love a woman who didn't love you, Cecil?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  A woman who didn't love me?  Oh, all my life!</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  So could I.  But it's so difficult to meet one.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  How can you be so conceited, DUMBY?</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  I didn't say it as a matter of conceit.  I said it as a 
matter of regret.  I have been wildly, madly adored.  I am sorry I 
have.  It has been an immense nuisance.  I should like to be 
allowed a little time to myself now and then.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Looking round.]</stagedir>  Time to educate yourself, I 
suppose.</speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  No, time to forget all I have learned.  That is much more 
important, dear Tuppy.  <stagedir>[LORD AUGUSTUS moves uneasily in his 
chair.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  What cynics you fellows are!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  What is a cynic?  <stagedir>[Sitting on the back of the sofa.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  A man who knows the price of everything and the 
value of nothing.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  And a sentimentalist, my dear Darlington, is a man 
who sees an absurd value in everything, and doesn't know the market 
price of any single thing.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You always amuse me, Cecil.  You talk as if you 
were a man of experience.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  I am.  <stagedir>[Moves up to front off fireplace.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You are far too young!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  That is a great error.  Experience is a question of 
instinct about life.  I have got it.  Tuppy hasn't.  Experience is 
the name Tuppy gives to his mistakes.  That is all.  <stagedir>[LORD AUGUSTUS 
looks round indignantly.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Experience is the name every one gives to their mistakes.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Standing with his back to the fireplace.]</stagedir>  One 
shouldn't commit any.  <stagedir>[Sees LADY WINDERMERE'S fan on sofa.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  Life would be very dull without them.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Of course you are quite faithful to this woman you 
are in love with, Darlington, to this good woman?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Cecil, if on really loves a woman, all other 
women in the world become absolutely meaningless to one.  Love 
changes one - I am changed.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Dear me!  How very interesting!  Tuppy, I want to 
talk to you.  <stagedir>[LORD AUGUSTUS takes no notice.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>DUMBY.</speaker>  It's no use talking to Tuppy.  You might just as well talk 
to a brick wall.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  But I like talking to a brick wall - it's the only 
thing in the world that never contradicts me!  Tuppy!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Well, what is it?  What is it?  <stagedir>[Rising and going 
over to CECIL GRAHAM.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Come over here.  I want you particularly.  <stagedir>[Aside.]</stagedir>  
Darlington has been moralising and talking about the purity of 
love, and that sort of thing, and he has got some woman in his 
rooms all the time.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  No, really! really!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  <stagedir>[In a low voice.]</stagedir>  Yes, here is her fan.  <stagedir>[Points to 
the fan.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Chuckling.]</stagedir>  By Jove!  By Jove!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Up by door.]</stagedir>  I am really off now, Lord 
Darlington.  I am sorry you are leaving England so soon.  Pray call 
on us when you come back!  My wife and I will be charmed to see 
you!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Up sage with LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  I am afraid I 
shall be away for many years.  Good-night!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Arthur!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  What?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  I want to speak to you for a moment.  No, do come!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Putting on his coat.]</stagedir>  I can't - I'm off!</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  It is something very particular.  It will interest 
you enormously.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  It is some of your nonsense, Cecil.</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  It isn't!  It isn't really.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Going to him.]</stagedir>  My dear fellow, you mustn't go 
yet.  I have a lot to talk to you about.  And Cecil has something 
to show you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Walking over.]</stagedir>  Well, what is it?</speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  Darlington has got a woman here in his rooms.  Here 
is her fan.  Amusing, isn't it?  <stagedir>[A pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Good God!  <stagedir>[Seizes the fan - DUMBY rises.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>CECIL GRAHAM.</speaker>  What is the matter?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Lord Darlington!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Turning round.]</stagedir>  Yes!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  What is my wife's fan doing here in your rooms?  
Hands off, Cecil.  Don't touch me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  Your wife's fan?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, here it is!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Walking towards him.]</stagedir>  I don't know!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You must know.  I demand an explanation.  Don't 
hold me, you fool.  <stagedir>[To CECIL GRAHAM.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Aside.]</stagedir>  She is here after all!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Speak, sir!  Why is my wife's fan here?  Answer 
me!  By God!  I'll search your rooms, and if my wife's here, I'll -  
<stagedir>[Moves.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD DARLINGTON.</speaker>  You shall not search my rooms.  You have no right 
to do so.  I forbid you!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You scoundrel!  I'll not leave your room till I 
have searched every corner of it!  What moves behind that curtain?  
<stagedir>[Rushes towards the curtain C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Enters behind R.]</stagedir>  Lord Windermere!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne!</speech>

<stagedir>[Every one starts and turns round.  LADY WINDERMERE slips out from 
behind the curtain and glides from the room L.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  I am afraid I took your wife's fan in mistake for my 
own, when I was leaving your house to-night.  I am so sorry.  
<stagedir>[Takes fan from him.  LORD WINDERMERE looks at her in contempt.  
LORD DARLINGTON in mingled astonishment and anger.  LORD AUGUSTUS 
turns away.  The other men smile at each other.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>ACT DROP.</stagedir>

</act>

<act>

<speech>FOURTH ACT</speech>

<scndesc>SCENE - Same as in Act I.</scndesc>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Lying on sofa.]</stagedir>  How can I tell him?  I can't 
tell him.  It would kill me.  I wonder what happened after I 
escaped from that horrible room.  Perhaps she told them the true 
reason of her being there, and the real meaning of that - fatal fan 
of mine.  Oh, if he knows - how can I look him in the face again?  
He would never forgive me.  <stagedir>[Touches bell.]</stagedir>  How securely one 
thinks one lives - out of reach of temptation, sin, folly.  And 
then suddenly - Oh!  Life is terrible.  It rules us, we do not rule 
it.</speech>

<speech><stagedir>[Enter ROSALIE R.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>ROSALIE.</speaker>  Did your ladyship ring for me?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  Have you found out at what time Lord 
Windermere came in last night?</speech>

<speech><speaker>ROSALIE.</speaker>  His lordship did not come in till five o'clock.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Five o'clock?  He knocked at my door this 
morning, didn't he?</speech>

<speech><speaker>ROSALIE.</speaker>  Yes, my lady - at half-past nine.  I told him your 
ladyship was not awake yet.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Did he say anything?</speech>

<speech><speaker>ROSALIE.</speaker>  Something about your ladyship's fan.  I didn't quite 
catch what his lordship said.  Has the fan been lost, my lady?  I 
can't find it, and Parker says it was not left in any of the rooms.  
He has looked in all of them and on the terrace as well.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It doesn't matter.  Tell Parker not to trouble.  
That will do.</speech>

<stagedir>[Exit ROSALIE.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  She is sure to tell him.  I can fancy 
a person doing a wonderful act of self-sacrifice, doing it 
spontaneously, recklessly, nobly - and afterwards finding out that 
it costs too much.  Why should she hesitate between her ruin and 
mine? . . . How strange!  I would have publicly disgraced her in my 
own house.  She accepts public disgrace in the house of another to 
save me. . . . There is a bitter irony in things, a bitter irony in 
the way we talk of good and bad women. . . . Oh, what a lesson! and 
what a pity that in life we only get our lessons when they are of 
no use to us!  For even if she doesn't tell, I must.  Oh! the shame 
of it, the shame of it.  To tell it is to live through it all 
again.  Actions are the first tragedy in life, words are the 
second.  Words are perhaps the worst.  Words are merciless. . . Oh!  
<stagedir>[Starts as LORD WINDERMERE enters.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Kisses her.]</stagedir>  Margaret - how pale you look!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I slept very badly.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Sitting on sofa with her.]</stagedir>  I am so sorry.  I 
came in dreadfully late, and didn't like to wake you.  You are 
crying, dear.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, I am crying, for I have something to tell 
you, Arthur.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  My dear child, you are not well.  You've been 
doing too much.  Let us go away to the country.  You'll be all 
right at Selby.  The season is almost over.  There is no use 
staying on.  Poor darling!  We'll go away to-day, if you like.  
<stagedir>[Rises.]</stagedir>  We can easily catch the 3.40.  I'll send a wire to 
Fannen.  <stagedir>[Crosses and sits down at table to write a telegram.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes; let us go away to-day.  No; I can't go to-
day, Arthur.  There is some one I must see before I leave town - 
some one who has been kind to me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising and leaning over sofa.]</stagedir>  Kind to you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Far more than that.  <stagedir>[Rises and goes to him.]</stagedir>  I 
will tell you, Arthur, but only love me, love me as you used to 
love me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Used to?  You are not thinking of that wretched 
woman who came here last night?  <stagedir>[Coming round and sitting R. of 
her.]</stagedir>  You don't still imagine - no, you couldn't.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I don't.  I know now I was wrong and foolish.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It was very good of you to receive her last night 
- but you are never to see her again.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why do you say that?  <stagedir>[A pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Holding her hand.]</stagedir>  Margaret, I thought Mrs. 
Erlynne was a woman more sinned against than sinning, as the phrase 
goes.  I thought she wanted to be good, to get back into a place 
that she had lost by a moment's folly, to lead again a decent life.  
I believed what she told me - I was mistaken in her.  She is bad - 
as bad as a woman can be.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Arthur, Arthur, don't talk so bitterly about any 
woman.  I don't think now that people can be divided into the good 
and the bad as though they were two sespeechte races or creations.  
What are called good women may have terrible things in them, mad 
moods of recklessness, assertion, jealousy, sin.  Bad women, as 
they are termed, may have in them sorrow, repentance, pity, 
sacrifice.  And I don't think Mrs. Erlynne a bad woman - I know 
she's not.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  My dear child, the woman's impossible.  No matter 
what harm she tries to do us, you must never see her again.  She is 
inadmissible anywhere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  But I want to see her.  I want her to come here.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Never!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  She came here once as YOUR guest.  She must come 
now as MINE.  That is but fair.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  She should never have come here.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  It is too late, Arthur, to say that 
now.  <stagedir>[Moves away.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  Margaret, if you knew where Mrs. 
Erlynne went last night, after she left this house, you would not 
sit in the same room with her.  It was absolutely shameless, the 
whole thing.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Arthur, I can't bear it any longer.  I must tell 
you.  Last night -</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER with a tray on which lie LADY WINDERMERE'S fan and a 
card.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne has called to return your ladyship's fan 
which she took away by mistake last night.  Mrs. Erlynne has 
written a message on the card.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh, ask Mrs. Erlynne to be kind enough to come 
up.  <stagedir>[Reads card.]</stagedir>  Say I shall be very glad to see her.  <stagedir>[Exit 
PARKER.]</stagedir>  She wants to see me, Arthur.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Takes card and looks at it.]</stagedir>  Margaret, I BEG 
you not to.  Let me see her first, at any rate.  She's a very 
dangerous woman.  She is the most dangerous woman I know.  You 
don't realise what you're doing.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  It is right that I should see her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  My child, you may be on the brink of a great 
sorrow.  Don't go to meet it.  It is absolutely necessary that I 
should see her before you do.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why should it be necessary?</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter MRS. ERLYNNE.]</stagedir>

<stagedir>[Exit PARKER.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  How do you do, Lady Windermere?  <stagedir>[To LORD 
WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>  How do you do?  Do you know, Lady Windermere, I am so 
sorry about your fan.  I can't imagine how I made such a silly 
mistake.  Most stupid of me.  And as I was driving in your 
direction, I thought I would take the opportunity of returning your 
property in person with many apologies for my carelessness, and of 
bidding you good-bye.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Good-bye?  <stagedir>[Moves towards sofa with MRS. ERLYNNE 
and sits down beside her.]</stagedir>  Are you going away, then, Mrs. Erlynne?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes; I am going to live abroad again.  The English 
climate doesn't suit me.  My - heart is affected here, and that I 
don't like.  I prefer living in the south.  London is too full of 
fogs and - and serious people, Lord Windermere.  Whether the fogs 
produce the serious people or whether the serious people produce 
the fogs, I don't know, but the whole thing rather gets on my 
nerves, and so I'm leaving this afternoon by the Club Train.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  This afternoon?  But I wanted so much to come and 
see you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  How kind of you!  But I am afraid I have to go.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Shall I never see you again, Mrs. Erlynne?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  I am afraid not.  Our lives lie too far apart.  But 
there is a little thing I would like you to do for me.  I want a 
photograph of you, Lady Windermere - would you give me one?  You 
don't know how gratified I should be.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh, with pleasure.  There is one on that table.  
I'll show it to you. <stagedir>[Goes across to the table.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coming up to MRS. ERLYNNE and speaking in a low 
voice.]</stagedir>  It is monstrous your intruding yourself here after your 
conduct last night.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With an amused smile.]</stagedir>  My dear Windermere, manners 
before morals!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Returning.]</stagedir>  I'm afraid it is very flattering - 
I am not so pretty as that.  <stagedir>[Showing photograph.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  You are much prettier.  But haven't you got one of 
yourself with your little boy?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I have.  Would you prefer one of those?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I'll go and get it for you, if you'll excuse me 
for a moment.  I have one upstairs.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  So sorry, Lady Windermere, to give you so much 
trouble.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Moves to door R.]</stagedir>  No trouble at all, Mrs. 
Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Thanks so much.

<stagedir>[Exit LADY WINDERMERE R.]</stagedir>  You seem rather out of temper this 
morning, Windermere.  Why should you be?  Margaret and I get on 
charmingly together.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I can't bear to see you with her.  Besides, you 
have not told me the truth, Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  I have not told HER the truth, you mean.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Standing C.]</stagedir>  I sometimes wish you had.  I 
should have been spared then the misery, the anxiety, the annoyance 
of the last six months.  But rather than my wife should know - that 
the mother whom she was taught to consider as dead, the mother whom 
she has mourned as dead, is living - a divorced woman, going about 
under an assumed name, a bad woman preying upon life, as I know you 
now to be - rather than that, I was ready to supply you with money 
to pay bill after bill, extravagance after extravagance, to risk 
what occurred yesterday, the first quarrel I have ever had with my 
wife.  You don't understand what that means to me.  How could you?  
But I tell you that the only bitter words that ever came from those 
sweet lips of hers were on your account, and I hate to see you next 
her.  You sully the innocence that is in her. <stagedir>[Moves L.C.]</stagedir>  And 
then I used to think that with all your faults you were frank and 
honest.  You are not.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Why do you say that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You made me get you an invitation to my wife's 
ball.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  For my daughter's ball - yes.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You came, and within an hour of your leaving the 
house you are found in a man's rooms - you are disgraced before 
every one.  <stagedir>[Goes up stage C.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Turning round on her.]</stagedir>  Therefore I have a right 
to look upon you as what you are - a worthless, vicious woman.  I 
have the right to tell you never to enter this house, never to 
attempt to come near my wife -</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coldly.]</stagedir>  My daughter, you mean.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You have no right to claim her as your daughter.  
You left her, abandoned her when she was but a child in the cradle, 
abandoned her for your lover, who abandoned you in turn.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  Do you count that to his credit, Lord 
Windermere - or to mine?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  To his, now that I know you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Take care - you had better be careful.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh, I am not going to mince words for you.  I 
know you thoroughly.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Looks steadily at him.]</stagedir>  I question that.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I DO know you.  For twenty years of your life you 
lived without your child, without a thought of your child.  One day 
you read in the papers that she had married a rich man.  You saw 
your hideous chance.  You knew that to spare her the ignominy of 
learning that a woman like you was her mother, I would endure 
anything.  You began your blackmailing,</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Shrugging her shoulders.]</stagedir>  Don't use ugly words, 
Windermere.  They are vulgar.  I saw my chance, it is true, and 
took it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, you took it - and spoiled it all last night 
by being found out.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a strange smile.]</stagedir>  You are quite right, I 
spoiled it all last night.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  And as for your blunder in taking my wife's fan 
from here and then leaving it about in Darlington's rooms, it is 
unpardonable.  I can't bear the sight of it now.  I shall never let 
my wife use it again.  The thing is soiled for me.  You should have 
kept it and not brought it back.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  I think I shall keep it.  <stagedir>[Goes up.]</stagedir>  It's extremely 
pretty.  <stagedir>[Takes up fan.]</stagedir>  I shall ask Margaret to give it to me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I hope my wife will give it you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Oh, I'm sure she will have no objection.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I wish that at the same time she would give you a 
miniature she kisses every night before she prays - It's the 
miniature of a young innocent-looking girl with beautiful DARK 
hair.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Ah, yes, I remember.  How long ago that seems!  
<stagedir>[Goes to sofa and sits down.]</stagedir>  It was done before I was married.  
Dark hair and an innocent expression were the fashion then, 
Windermere!  <stagedir>[A pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  What do you mean by coming here this morning?  
What is your object?  <stagedir>[Crossing L.C. and sitting.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a note of irony in her voice.]</stagedir>  To bid good-
bye to my dear daughter, of course.  <stagedir>[LORD WINDERMERE bites his 
under lip in anger.  MRS. ERLYNNE looks at him, and her voice and 
manner become serious.  In her accents at she talks there is a note 
of deep tragedy.  For a moment she reveals herself.]</stagedir>  Oh, don't 
imagine I am going to have a pathetic scene with her, weep on her 
neck and tell her who I am, and all that kind of thing.  I have no 
ambition to play the part of a mother.  Only once in my life like I 
known a mother's feelings.  That was last night.  They were 
terrible - they made me suffer - they made me suffer too much.  For 
twenty years, as you say, I have lived childless, - I want to live 
childless still.  <stagedir>[Hiding her feelings with a trivial laugh.]</stagedir>  
Besides, my dear Windermere, how on earth could I pose as a mother 
with a grown-up daughter?  Margaret is twenty-one, and I have never 
admitted that I am more than twenty-nine, or thirty at the most.  
Twenty-nine when there are pink shades, thirty when there are not.  
So you see what difficulties it would involve.  No, as far as I am 
concerned, let your wife cherish the memory of this dead, stainless 
mother.  Why should I interfere with her illusions?  I find it hard 
enough to keep my own.  I lost one illusion last night.  I thought 
I had no heart.  I find I have, and a heart doesn't suit me, 
Windermere.  Somehow it doesn't go with modern dress.  It makes one 
look old.  <stagedir>[Takes up hand-mirror from table and looks into it.]</stagedir>  
And it spoils one's career at critical moments.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You fill me with horror - with absolute horror.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  I suppose, Windermere, you would like me 
to retire into a convent, or become a hospital nurse, or something 
of that kind, as people do in silly modern novels.  That is stupid 
of you, Arthur; in real life we don't do such things - not as long 
as we have any good looks left, at any rate.  No - what consoles 
one nowadays is not repentance, but pleasure.  Repentance is quite 
out of date.  And besides, if a woman really repents, she has to go 
to a bad dressmaker, otherwise no one believes in her.  And nothing 
in the world would induce me to do that.  No; I am going to pass 
entirely out of your two lives.  My coming into them has been a 
mistake - I discovered that last night.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  A fatal mistake.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling.]</stagedir>  Almost fatal.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am sorry now I did not tell my wife the whole 
thing at once.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  I regret my bad actions.  You regret your good ones 
- that is the difference between us.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I don't trust you.  I WILL tell my wife.  It's 
better for her to know, and from me.  It will cause her infinite 
pain - it will humiliate her terribly, but it's right that she 
should know.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  You propose to tell her?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am going to tell her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Going up to him.]</stagedir>  If you do, I will make my name 
so infamous that it will mar every moment of her life.  It will 
ruin her, and make her wretched.  If you dare to tell her, there is 
no depth of degradation I will not sink to, no pit of shame I will 
not enter.  You shall not tell her - I forbid you.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Why?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[After a pause.]</stagedir>  If I said to you that I cared for 
her, perhaps loved her even - you would sneer at me, wouldn't you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I should feel it was not true.  A mother's love 
means devotion, unselfishness, sacrifice.  What could you know of 
such things?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  You are right.  What could I know of such things?  
Don't let us talk any more about it - as for telling my daughter 
who I am, that I do not allow.  It is my secret, it is not yours.  
If I make up my mind to tell her, and I think I will, I shall tell 
her before I leave the house - if not, I shall never tell her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Angrily.]</stagedir>  Then let me beg of you to leave our 
house at once.  I will make your excuses to Margaret.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LADY WINDERMERE R.  She goes over to MRS. ERLYNNE with the 
photograph in her hand.  LORD WINDERMERE moves to back of sofa, and 
anxiously watches MRS. ERLYNNE as the scene progresses.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I am so sorry, Mrs. Erlynne, to have kept you 
waiting.  I couldn't find the photograph anywhere.  At last I 
discovered it in my husband's dressing-room - he had stolen it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Takes the photograph from her and looks at it.]</stagedir>  I 
am not surprised - it is charming.  <stagedir>[Goes over to sofa with LADY 
WINDERMERE, and sits down beside her.  Looks again at the 
photograph.]</stagedir>  And so that is your little boy!  What is he called?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Gerard, after my dear father.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Laying the photograph down.]</stagedir>  Really?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  If it had been a girl, I would have called 
it after my mother.  My mother had the same name as myself, 
Margaret.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  My name is Margaret too.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Indeed!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes.  <stagedir>[Pause.]</stagedir>  You are devoted to your mother's 
memory, Lady Windermere, your husband tells me.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  We all have ideals in life.  At least we all 
should have.  Mine is my mother.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Ideals are dangerous things.  Realities are better.  
They wound, but they're better.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Shaking her head.]</stagedir>  If I lost my ideals, I 
should lose everything.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Everything?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes.  <stagedir>[Pause.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Did your father often speak to you of your mother?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  No, it gave him too much pain.  He told me how my 
mother had died a few months after I was born.  His eyes filled 
with tears as he spoke.  Then he begged me never to mention her 
name to him again.  It made him suffer even to hear it.  My father 
- my father really died of a broken heart.  His was the most ruined 
life know,</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  I am afraid I must go now, Lady 
Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Rising.]</stagedir>  Oh no, don't.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  I think I had better.  My carriage must have come 
back by this time.  I sent it to Lady Jedburgh's with a note.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Arthur, would you mind seeing if Mrs. Erlynne's 
carriage has come back?</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Pray don't trouble, Lord Windermere.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Yes, Arthur, do go, please.</speech>

<stagedir>[LORD WINDERMERE hesitated for a moment and looks at MRS. ERLYNNE.  
She remains quite impassive.  He leaves the room.]</stagedir>

<speech><stagedir>[To MRS. ERLYNNE.]</stagedir>  Oh!  What am I to say to you?  You saved me 
last night?  <stagedir>[Goes towards her.]</stagedir></speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Hush - don't speak of it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I must speak of it.  I can't let you think that I 
am going to accept this sacrifice.  I am not.  It is too great.  I 
am going to tell my husband everything.  It is my duty.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  It is not your duty - at least you have duties to 
others besides him.  You say you owe me something?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  I owe you everything.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Then pay your debt by silence.  That is the only way 
in which it can be paid.  Don't spoil the one good thing I have 
done in my life by telling it to any one.  Promise me that what 
passed last night will remain a secret between us.  You must not 
bring misery into your husband's life.  Why spoil his love?  You 
must not spoil it.  Love is easily killed.  Oh! how easily love is 
killed.  Pledge me your word, Lady Windermere, that you will never 
tell him.  I insist upon it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With bowed head.]</stagedir>  It is your will, not mine.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Yes, it is my will.  And never forget your child - I 
like to think of you as a mother.  I like you to think of yourself 
as one.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Looking up.]</stagedir>  I always will now.  Only once in 
my life I have forgotten my own mother - that was last night.  Oh, 
if I had remembered her I should not have been so foolish, so 
wicked.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[With a slight shudder.]</stagedir>  Hush, last night is quite 
over.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD WINDERMERE.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Your carriage has not come back yet, Mrs. 
Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  It makes no matter.  I'll take a hansom.  There is 
nothing in the world so respectable as a good Shrewsbury and 
Talbot.  And now, dear Lady Windermere, I am afraid it is really 
good-bye.  <stagedir>[Moves up C.]</stagedir>  Oh, I remember.  You'll think me absurd, 
but do you know I've taken a great fancy to this fan that I was 
silly enough to run away with last night from your ball.  Now, I 
wonder would you give it to me?  Lord Windermere says you may.  I 
know it is his present.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh, certainly, if it will give you any pleasure.  
But it has my name on it.  It has 'Margaret' on it.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  But we have the same Christian name.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Oh, I forgot.  Of course, do have it.  What a 
wonderful chance our names being the same!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  Quite wonderful.  Thanks - it will always remind me 
of you.  <stagedir>[Shakes hands with her.]</stagedir></speech>

<stagedir>[Enter PARKER.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>PARKER.</speaker>  Lord Augustus Lorton.  Mrs. Erlynne's carriage has come.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD AUGUSTUS.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Good morning, dear boy.  Good morning, Lady 
Windermere.  <stagedir>[Sees MRS. ERLYNNE.]</stagedir>  Mrs. Erlynne!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  How do you do, Lord Augustus?  Are you quite well 
this morning?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Coldly.]</stagedir>  Quite well, thank you, Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  You don't look at all well, Lord Augustus.  You stop 
up too late - it is so bad for you.  You really should take more 
care of yourself.  Good-bye, Lord Windermere. <stagedir>[Goes towards door 
with a bow to LORD AUGUSTUS.  Suddenly smiles and looks back at 
him.]</stagedir>  Lord Augustus!  Won't you see me to my carriage?  You might 
carry the fan.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Allow me!</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  No; I want Lord Augustus.  I have a special message 
for the dear Duchess.  Won't you carry the fan, Lord Augustus?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  If you really desire it, Mrs. Erlynne.</speech>

<speech><speaker>MRS. ERLYNNE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Laughing.]</stagedir>  Of course I do.  You'll carry it so 
gracefully.  You would carry off anything gracefully, dear Lord 
Augustus.</speech>

<stagedir>[When she reaches the door she looks back for a moment at LADY 
WINDERMERE.  Their eyes meet.  Then she turns, and exit C. followed 
by LORD AUGUSTUS.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  You will never speak against Mrs. Erlynne again, 
Arthur, will you?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Gravely.]</stagedir>  She is better than one thought her.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  She is better than I am.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Smiling as he strokes her hair.]</stagedir>  Child, you and 
she belong to different worlds.  Into your world evil has never 
entered.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Don't say that, Arthur.  There is the same world 
for all of us, and good and evil, sin and innocence, go through it 
hand in hand.  To shut one's eyes to half of life that one may live 
securely is as though one blinded oneself that one might walk with 
more safety in a land of pit and precipice.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Moves down with her.]</stagedir>  Darling, why do you say 
that?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Sits on sofa.]</stagedir>  Because I, who had shut my eyes 
to life, came to the brink.  And one who had sespeechted us -</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  We were never sespeechted.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  We never must be again.  O Arthur, don't love me 
less, and I will trust you more.  I will trust you absolutely.  Let 
us go to Selby.  In the Rose Garden at Selby the roses are white 
and red.</speech>

<stagedir>[Enter LORD AUGUSTUS C.]</stagedir>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  Arthur, she has explained everything!

<stagedir>[LADY WINDERMERE looks horribly frightened at this.  LORD 
WINDERMERE starts.  LORD AUGUSTUS takes WINDERMERE by the arm and 
brings him to front of stage.  He talks rapidly and in a low voice.  
LADY WINDERMERE stands watching them in terror.]</stagedir>  My dear fellow, 
she has explained every demmed thing.  We all wronged her 
immensely.  It was entirely for my sake she went to Darlington's 
rooms.  Called first at the Club - fact is, wanted to put me out of 
suspense - and being told I had gone on - followed - naturally 
frightened when she heard a lot of us coming in - retired to 
another room - I assure you, most gratifying to me, the whole 
thing.  We all behaved brutally to her.  She is just the woman for 
me.  Suits me down to the ground.  All the conditions she makes are 
that we live entirely out of England.  A very good thing too.  
Demmed clubs, demmed climate, demmed cooks, demmed everything.  
Sick of it all!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Frightened.]</stagedir>  Has Mrs. Erlynne - ?</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD AUGUSTUS.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Advancing towards her with a low bow.]</stagedir>  Yes, Lady 
Windermere -  Mrs. Erlynne has done me the honour of accepting my 
hand.</speech>

<speech><speaker>LORD WINDERMERE.</speaker>  Well, you are certainly marrying a very clever 
woman!</speech>

<speech><speaker>LADY WINDERMERE.</speaker>  <stagedir>[Taking her husband's hand.]</stagedir>  Ah, you're marrying 
a very good woman!</speech>

<stagedir>CURTAIN</stagedir>

</act>

</playbody>

</play>

<endgutblurb>
<para>End of The Project Gutenberg Etext of Lady Windermere's Fan, by Wilde</para>
</endgutblurb>

</gutplay>
