<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE gutbook SYSTEM "gutbook1.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="darwin.css"?>

<gutbook>
<gutblurb>
<para>
The Project Gutenberg Etext of The Masque of the Red Death by Edgar Allan Poe
</para>

<para>
#4 in our series by Edgar Allan Poe
#1 is The Fall of the House of Usher, June, 1997, Etext #932.
Filenames that are usher*.*
</para>

<para>
This is our second experimental effort at cataloguing multiple
items in a single file.  In the first instance we use the same
index number for each item, and just used multiple entries for
that file in the index.  In this, the second instance, we have
used separate index numbers for the collection and for all the
entries in that collection.  Let us know which you prefer.  We
have traditionally used the smallest number of index entries--
as somewhat of a protest against others who have copied Etexts
and wanted it to appear as if they had more Etext than Project
Gutenberg or various other etext collections.  We want to make
our Etexts as easy as possible to find and work with, but, not
to "pad" our work.  However, we prefer to post short works for
you in collections, to eliminate you having to download all 11
kilobytes of our header and "legal fine print" to get files of
sizes less than the headers. Please email me on this.  Thanks!
Michael S. Hart, hart@pobox.com
</para>

<para>
Copyright laws are changing all over the world, be sure to check
the copyright laws for your country before posting these files!!
</para>

<para>
Please take a look at the important information in this header.
We encourage you to keep this file on your own disk, keeping an
electronic path open for the next readers.  Do not remove this.
</para>

<para>
**Welcome To The World of Free Plain Vanilla Electronic Texts**
**Etexts Readable By Both Humans and By Computers, Since 1971**
*These Etexts Prepared By Hundreds of Volunteers and Donations*
</para>

<para>
Information on contacting Project Gutenberg to get Etexts, and
further information is included below.  We need your donations.
</para>

<para>
The Masque of the Red Death
</para>

<para>
by Edgar Allan Poe
</para>

<para>
October, 1997  [Etexts #1064]
</para>

<para>
The Project Gutenberg Etext of The Masque of the Red Death by Edgar Allan Poe
******This file should be named 1epoe10.txt or 1epoe10.zip*****
</para>

<para>
Corrected EDITIONS of our etexts get a new NUMBER, 1epoe11.txt.
VERSIONS based on separate sources get new LETTER, 1epoe10a.txt.
</para>

<para>
Scanned and proofread by Levent Kurnaz
</para>

<para>
Project Gutenberg Etexts are usually created from multiple editions,
all of which are in the Public Domain in the United States, unless a
copyright notice is included.  Therefore, we do NOT keep these books
in compliance with any particular paper edition, usually otherwise.
</para>

<para>
We are now trying to release all our books one month in advance
of the official release dates, for time for better editing.
</para>

<para>
Please note:  neither this list nor its contents are final till
midnight of the last day of the month of any such announcement.
The official release date of all Project Gutenberg Etexts is at
Midnight, Central Time, of the last day of the stated month.  A
preliminary version may often be posted for suggestion, comment
and editing by those who wish to do so.  To be sure you have an
up to date first edition [xxxxx10x.xxx] please check file sizes
in the first week of the next month.  Since our ftp program has
a bug in it that scrambles the date [tried to fix and failed] a
look at the file size will have to do, but we will try to see a
new copy has at least one byte more or less.
</para>

<para>
Information about Project Gutenberg (one page)
</para>

<para>
We produce about two million dollars for each hour we work.  The
fifty hours is one conservative estimate for how long it we take
to get any etext selected, entered, proofread, edited, copyright
searched and analyzed, the copyright letters written, etc.  This
projected audience is one hundred million readers.  If our value
per text is nominally estimated at one dollar then we produce $2
million dollars per hour this year as we release thirty-two text
files per month, or 384 more Etexts in 1997 for a total of 1000+
If these reach just 10% of the computerized population, then the
total should reach over 100 billion Etexts given away.
</para>

<para>
The Goal of Project Gutenberg is to Give Away One Trillion Etext
Files by the December 31, 2001.  [10,000 x 100,000,000=Trillion]
This is ten thousand titles each to one hundred million readers,
which is only 10% of the present number of computer users.  2001
should have at least twice as many computer users as that, so it
will require us reaching less than 5% of the users in 2001.
</para>

<para>
We need your donations more than ever!
</para>

<para>
All donations should be made to "Project Gutenberg/CMU": and are
tax deductible to the extent allowable by law.  (CMU = Carnegie-
Mellon University).
</para>

<para>
For these and other matters, please mail to:
</para>

<para>
Project Gutenberg
P. O. Box  2782
Champaign, IL 61825
</para>

<para>
When all other email fails try our Executive Director:
Michael S. Hart hart@pobox.com
</para>

<para>
We would prefer to send you this information by email
(Internet, Bitnet, Compuserve, ATTMAIL or MCImail).
</para>

<para>
******
If you have an FTP program (or emulator), please
FTP directly to the Project Gutenberg archives:
[Mac users, do NOT point and click. . .type]
</para>

<para>
ftp uiarchive.cso.uiuc.edu
login:  anonymous
password:  your@login
cd etext/etext90 through /etext96
or cd etext/articles [get suggest gut for more information]
dir [to see files]
get or mget [to get files. . .set bin for zip files]
GET INDEX?00.GUT
for a list of books
and
GET NEW GUT for general information
and
MGET GUT* for newsletters.
</para>

<para>
**Information prepared by the Project Gutenberg legal advisor**
(Three Pages)
</para>

<para>
***START**THE SMALL PRINT!**FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN ETEXTS**START***
Why is this "Small Print!" statement here?  You know: lawyers.
They tell us you might sue us if there is something wrong with
your copy of this etext, even if you got it for free from
someone other than us, and even if what's wrong is not our
fault.  So, among other things, this "Small Print!" statement
disclaims most of our liability to you.  It also tells you how
you can distribute copies of this etext if you want to.
</para>

<para>
*BEFORE!* YOU USE OR READ THIS ETEXT
By using or reading any part of this PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm
etext, you indicate that you understand, agree to and accept
this "Small Print!" statement.  If you do not, you can receive
a refund of the money (if any) you paid for this etext by
sending a request within 30 days of receiving it to the person
you got it from.  If you received this etext on a physical
medium (such as a disk), you must return it with your request.
</para>

<para>
ABOUT PROJECT GUTENBERG-TM ETEXTS
This PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext, like most PROJECT GUTENBERG-
tm etexts, is a "public domain" work distributed by Professor
Michael S. Hart through the Project Gutenberg Association at
Carnegie-Mellon University (the "Project").  Among other
things, this means that no one owns a United States copyright
on or for this work, so the Project (and you!) can copy and
distribute it in the United States without permission and
without paying copyright royalties.  Special rules, set forth
below, apply if you wish to copy and distribute this etext
under the Project's "PROJECT GUTENBERG" trademark.
</para>

<para>
To create these etexts, the Project expends considerable
efforts to identify, transcribe and proofread public domain
works.  Despite these efforts, the Project's etexts and any
medium they may be on may contain "Defects".  Among other
things, Defects may take the form of incomplete, inaccurate or
corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other
intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged
disk or other etext medium, a computer virus, or computer
codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment.
</para>

<para>
LIMITED WARRANTY; DISCLAIMER OF DAMAGES
But for the "Right of Replacement or Refund" described below,
[1] the Project (and any other party you may receive this
etext from as a PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext) disclaims all
liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including
legal fees, and [2] YOU HAVE NO REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE OR
UNDER STRICT LIABILITY, OR FOR BREACH OF WARRANTY OR CONTRACT,
INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO INDIRECT, CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE
OR INCIDENTAL DAMAGES, EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE
POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.
</para>

<para>
If you discover a Defect in this etext within 90 days of
receiving it, you can receive a refund of the money (if any)
you paid for it by sending an explanatory note within that
time to the person you received it from.  If you received it
on a physical medium, you must return it with your note, and
such person may choose to alternatively give you a replacement
copy.  If you received it electronically, such person may
choose to alternatively give you a second opportunity to
receive it electronically.
</para>

<para>
THIS ETEXT IS OTHERWISE PROVIDED TO YOU "AS-IS".  NO OTHER
WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, ARE MADE TO YOU AS
TO THE ETEXT OR ANY MEDIUM IT MAY BE ON, INCLUDING BUT NOT
LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A
PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</para>

<para>
Some states do not allow disclaimers of implied warranties or
the exclusion or limitation of consequential damages, so the
above disclaimers and exclusions may not apply to you, and you
may have other legal rights.
</para>

<para>
INDEMNITY
You will indemnify and hold the Project, its directors,
officers, members and agents harmless from all liability, cost
and expense, including legal fees, that arise directly or
indirectly from any of the following that you do or cause:
[1] distribution of this etext, [2] alteration, modification,
or addition to the etext, or [3] any Defect.
</para>

<para>
DISTRIBUTION UNDER "PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm"
You may distribute copies of this etext electronically, or by
disk, book or any other medium if you either delete this
"Small Print!" and all other references to Project Gutenberg,
or:
</para>

<para>
[1]  Only give exact copies of it.  Among other things, this
     requires that you do not remove, alter or modify the
     etext or this "small print!" statement.  You may however,
     if you wish, distribute this etext in machine readable
     binary, compressed, mark-up, or proprietary form,
     including any form resulting from conversion by word pro-
     cessing or hypertext software, but only so long as
     *EITHER*:
</para>

<para>
     [*]  The etext, when displayed, is clearly readable, and
          does *not* contain characters other than those
          intended by the author of the work, although tilde
          (~), asterisk (*) and underline (_) characters may
          be used to convey punctuation intended by the
          author, and additional characters may be used to
          indicate hypertext links; OR
</para>

<para>
     [*]  The etext may be readily converted by the reader at
          no expense into plain ASCII, EBCDIC or equivalent
          form by the program that displays the etext (as is
          the case, for instance, with most word processors);
          OR
</para>

<para>
     [*]  You provide, or agree to also provide on request at
          no additional cost, fee or expense, a copy of the
          etext in its original plain ASCII form (or in EBCDIC
          or other equivalent proprietary form).
</para>

<para>
[2]  Honor the etext refund and replacement provisions of this
     "Small Print!" statement.
</para>

<para>
[3]  Pay a trademark license fee to the Project of 20% of the
     net profits you derive calculated using the method you
     already use to calculate your applicable taxes.  If you
     don't derive profits, no royalty is due.  Royalties are
     payable to "Project Gutenberg Association/Carnegie-Mellon
     University" within the 60 days following each
     date you prepare (or were legally required to prepare)
     your annual (or equivalent periodic) tax return.
</para>

<para>
WHAT IF YOU *WANT* TO SEND MONEY EVEN IF YOU DON'T HAVE TO?
The Project gratefully accepts contributions in money, time,
scanning machines, OCR software, public domain etexts, royalty
free copyright licenses, and every other sort of contribution
you can think of.  Money should be paid to "Project Gutenberg
Association / Carnegie-Mellon University".
</para>

<para>
*END*THE SMALL PRINT! FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN ETEXTS*Ver.04.29.93*END*
</para>
</gutblurb>

<markupblurb>
Scanned and proofread by Levent Kurnaz
Marked up by John Hanna Feb 2000
Validated against gutbook1.dtd using MSXML Feb 2000
Checked with IBM C parser Frank Boumphrey
</markupblurb>

<book>
<acknowledge>A project of the HTML Writers Guild and Project Gutenberg. Markup by an anonymous Project Gutenberg Volunteer, Markup by John Hanna Feb 2000</acknowledge>
<frontmatter>
<titlepage>
<title>The Masque of the Red Death</title>
<para>by</para>
<author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
<para>
October, 1997  [Etext #1064]*
</para>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<bookbody>
<part>
<chapter>

<para>
The "Red Death" had long devastated the country.  No
pestilence had ever been so fatal, or so hideous.  Blood was its
Avatar and its seal--the redness and the horror of blood.  There were
sharp pains, and sudden dizziness, and then profuse bleeding at the
pores, with dissolution.  The scarlet stains upon the body and
especially upon the face of the victim, were the pest ban which
shut him out from the aid and from the sympathy of his fellow-men.
And the whole seizure, progress and termination of the disease,
were the incidents of half an hour.
</para>

<para>
But the Prince Prospero was happy and dauntless and sagacious.
When his dominions were half depopulated, he summoned to his
presence a thousand hale and light-hearted friends from among the
knights and dames of his court, and with these retired to the deep
seclusion of one of his castellated abbeys.  This was an extensive
and magnificent structure, the creation of the prince's own
eccentric yet august taste.  A strong and lofty wall girdled it in.
This wall had gates of iron.  The courtiers, having entered,
brought furnaces and massy hammers and welded the bolts.  They
resolved to leave means neither of ingress nor egress to the sudden
impulses of despair or of frenzy from within.  The abbey was amply
provisioned.  With such precautions the courtiers might bid
defiance to contagion.  The external world could take care of
itself.  In the meantime it was folly to grieve, or to think.  The
prince had provided all the appliances of pleasure.  There were
buffoons, there were improvisatori, there were ballet-dancers,
there were musicians, there was Beauty, there was wine.  All these
and security were within.  Without was the "Red Death".
</para>

<para>
It was towards the close of the fifth or sixth month of his
seclusion, and while the pestilence raged most furiously
abroad, that the Prince Prospero entertained his thousand friends
at a masked ball of the most unusual magnificence.
</para>

<para>
It was a voluptuous scene, that masquerade.  But first let me
tell of the rooms in which it was held.  These were seven--an
imperial suite.  In many palaces, however, such suites form a long
and straight vista, while the folding doors slide back nearly to
the walls on either hand, so that the view of the whole extent is
scarcely impeded.  Here the case was very different, as might have
been expected from the duke's love of the  bizarre.  The
apartments were so irregularly disposed that the vision embraced
but little more than one at a time.  There was a sharp turn at
every twenty or thirty yards, and at each turn a novel effect.  To
the right and left, in the middle of each wall, a tall and narrow
Gothic window looked out upon a closed corridor which pursued the
windings of the suite.  These windows were of stained glass whose
colour varied in accordance with the prevailing hue of the
decorations of the chamber into which it opened.  That at the
eastern extremity was hung, for example in blue--and vividly blue
were its windows.  The second chamber was purple in its ornaments
and tapestries, and here the panes were purple.  The third was
green throughout, and so were the casements.  The fourth was
furnished and lighted with orange--the fifth with white--the sixth
with violet.  The seventh apartment was closely shrouded in black
velvet tapestries that hung all over the ceiling and down the
walls, falling in heavy folds upon a carpet of the same material
and hue.  But in this chamber only, the colour of the windows
failed to correspond with the decorations.  The panes here were
scarlet--a deep blood colour.  Now in no one of the seven
apartments was there any lamp or candelabrum, amid the profusion of
golden ornaments that lay scattered to and fro or depended from the
roof.  There was no light of any kind emanating from lamp or candle
within the suite of chambers.  But in the corridors that followed
the suite, there stood, opposite to each window, a heavy tripod,
bearing a brazier of fire, that projected its rays through the
tinted glass and so glaringly illumined the room.  And thus were
produced a multitude of gaudy and fantastic appearances.  But in
the western or black chamber the effect of the fire-light that
streamed upon the dark hangings through the blood-tinted panes,
was ghastly in the extreme, and produced so wild a look upon the
countenances of those who entered, that there were few of the
company bold enough to set foot within its precincts at all.
</para>

<para>
It was in this apartment, also, that there stood against the
western wall, a gigantic clock of ebony.  Its pendulum swung to and
fro with a dull, heavy, monotonous clang; and when the minute-hand
made the circuit of the face, and the hour was to be stricken,
there came from the brazen lungs of the clock a sound which was
clear and loud and deep and exceedingly musical, but of so peculiar
a note and emphasis that, at each lapse of an hour, the musicians
of the orchestra were constrained to pause, momentarily, in their
performance, to harken to the sound; and thus the waltzers perforce
ceased their evolutions; and there was a brief disconcert of the
whole gay company; and, while the chimes of the clock yet rang, it
was observed that the giddiest grew pale, and the more aged and
sedate passed their hands over their brows as if in confused
revery or meditation.  But when the echoes had fully ceased, a
light laughter at once pervaded the assembly; the musicians looked
at each other and smiled as if at their own nervousness and folly,
and made whispering vows, each to the other, that the next chiming
of the clock should produce in them no similar emotion; and then,
after the lapse of sixty minutes, (which embrace three thousand and
six hundred seconds of the Time that flies,) there came yet another
chiming of the clock, and then were the same disconcert and
tremulousness and meditation as before.
</para>

<para>
But, in spite of these things, it was a gay and magnificent
revel.  The tastes of the duke were peculiar.  He had a fine eye
for colours and effects.  He disregarded the  decora of mere
fashion.  His plans were bold and fiery, and his conceptions glowed
with barbaric lustre.  There are some who would have thought him
mad.  His followers felt that he was not.  It was necessary to hear
and see and touch him to be  sure that he was not.
</para>

<para>
He had directed, in great part, the movable embellishments of
the seven chambers, upon occasion of this great  fete; and it
was his own guiding taste which had given character to the
masqueraders.  Be sure they were grotesque.  There were much glare
and glitter and piquancy and phantasm--much of what has been since
 seen in  "Hernani".  There were arabesque figures with
unsuited limbs and appointments.  There were delirious fancies such
as the madman fashions.  There were much of the beautiful, much of
the wanton, much of the  bizarre, something of the terrible, and
not a little of that which might have excited disgust.  To and fro
in the seven chambers there stalked, in fact, a multitude of
dreams.  And these--the dreams--writhed in and about taking hue
from the rooms, and causing the wild music of the orchestra to seem
as the echo of their steps.  And, anon, there strikes the ebony
clock which stands in the hall of the velvet.  And then, for a
moment, all is still, and all is silent save the voice of the
clock.  The dreams are stiff-frozen as they stand.  But the echoes
of the chime die away--they have endured but an instant--and a
light, half-subdued laughter floats after them as they depart.  And
now again the music swells, and the dreams live, and writhe to and
fro more merrily than ever, taking hue from the many tinted windows
through which stream the rays from the tripods.  But to the chamber
which lies most westwardly of the seven, there are now none of the
maskers who venture; for the night is waning away; and there flows
a ruddier light through the blood-coloured panes; and the blackness
of the sable drapery appals; and to him whose foot falls upon the
sable carpet, there comes from the near clock of ebony a muffled
peal more solemnly emphatic than any which reaches  their ears
who indulged in the more remote gaieties of the other apartments.
</para>

<para>
But these other apartments were densely crowded, and in them
beat feverishly the heart of life.  And the revel went whirlingly
on, until at length there commenced the sounding of midnight upon
the clock.  And then the music ceased, as I have told; and the
evolutions of the waltzers were quieted; and there was an uneasy
cessation of all things as before.  But now there were twelve
strokes to be sounded by the bell of the clock; and thus it
happened, perhaps, that more of thought crept, with more of time,
into the meditations of the thoughtful among those who revelled.
And thus too, it happened, perhaps, that before the last echoes of
the last chime had utterly sunk into silence, there were many
individuals in the crowd who had found leisure to become aware of
the presence of a masked figure which had arrested the
attention of no single individual before.  And the rumour of this
new presence having spread itself whisperingly around, there arose
at length from the whole company a buzz, or murmur, expressive of
disapprobation and surprise--then, finally, of terror, of horror,
and of disgust.
</para>

<para>
In an assembly of phantasms such as I have painted, it may
well be supposed that no ordinary appearance could have excited
such sensation.  In truth the masquerade licence of the night was
nearly unlimited; but the figure in question had out-Heroded Herod,
and gone beyond the bounds of even the prince's indefinite decorum.
There are chords in the hearts of the most reckless which cannot be
touched without emotion.  Even with the utterly lost, to whom life
and death are equally jests, there are matters of which no jest can
be made.  The whole company, indeed, seemed now deeply to feel that
in the costume and bearing of the stranger neither wit nor
propriety existed.  The figure was tall and gaunt, and shrouded
from head to foot in the habiliments of the grave.  The mask which
concealed the visage was made so nearly to resemble the countenance
of a stiffened corpse that the closest scrutiny must have had
difficulty in detecting the cheat.  And yet all this might have
been endured, if not approved, by the mad revellers around.  But
the mummer had gone so far as to assume the type of the Red Death.
His vesture was dabbled in  blood--and his broad brow, with all
the features of the face, was besprinkled with the scarlet horror.
</para>

<para>
When the eyes of the Prince Prospero fell upon this spectral
image (which, with a slow and solemn movement, as if more fully to
sustain its  role, stalked to and fro among the waltzers) he was
seen to be convulsed, in the first moment with a strong shudder
either of terror or distaste; but, in the next, his brow reddened
with rage.
</para>

<para>
"Who dares,"--he demanded hoarsely of the courtiers who stood
near him--"who dares insult us with this blasphemous mockery?
Seize him and unmask him--that we may know whom we have to hang, at
sunrise, from the battlements!"
</para>

<para>
It was in the eastern or blue chamber in which stood the
Prince Prospero as he uttered these words.  They rang throughout
the seven rooms loudly and clearly, for the prince was a bold and
robust man, and the music had become hushed at the waving of his
hand.
</para>

<para>
It was in the blue room where stood the prince, with a group
of  pale courtiers by his side.  At first, as he spoke,
there was a slight rushing movement of this group in the direction
of the intruder, who at the moment was also near at hand, and now,
with deliberate and stately step, made closer approach to the
speaker.  But from a certain nameless awe with which the mad
assumptions of the mummer had inspired the whole party, there were
found none who put forth hand to seize him; so that, unimpeded, he
passed within a yard of the prince's person; and, while the vast
assembly, as if with one impulse, shrank from the centres of the
rooms to the walls, he made his way uninterruptedly, but with the
same solemn and measured step which had distinguished him from the
first, through the blue chamber to the purple--through the purple
to the green--through the green to the orange--through this again
to the white--and even thence to the violet, ere a decided movement
had been made to arrest him.  It was then, however, that the Prince
Prospero, maddening with rage and the shame of his own momentary
cowardice, rushed hurriedly through the six chambers, while none
followed him on account of a deadly terror that had seized upon
all.  He bore aloft a drawn dagger, and had approached, in rapid
impetuosity, to within three or four feet of the retreating figure,
when the latter, having attained the extremity of the velvet
apartment, turned suddenly and confronted his pursuer.  There was
a sharp cry--and the dagger dropped gleaming upon the sable carpet,
upon which, instantly afterwards, fell prostrate in death the
Prince Prospero.  Then, summoning the wild courage of despair, a
throng of the revellers at once threw themselves into the black
apartment, and, seizing the mummer, whose tall figure stood erect
and motionless within the shadow of the ebony clock, gasped in
unutterable horror at finding the grave cerements and corpse-like
mask, which they handled with so violent a rudeness, untenanted by
any tangible form.
</para>

<para>
And now was acknowledged the presence of the Red Death.  He
had come like a thief in the night.  And one by one dropped the
revellers in the blood-bedewed halls of their revel, and died each
in the despairing posture of his fall.  And the life of the ebony
clock went out with that of the last of the gay.  And the flames of
the tripods expired.  And Darkness and Decay and the Red Death held
illimitable dominion over all.
</para>

<para>
End of The Project Gutenberg Etext of
The Masque of the Red Death
by Edgar Allan Poe
</para>
</chapter>
</part>
</bookbody>
</book>
</gutbook>




